<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<feed xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:opensearch="http://a9.com/-/spec/opensearch/1.1/" xmlns:s="http://jadedpixel.com/-/spec/shopify">
  <id>https://stewarthill.co.uk/blogs/news.atom</id>
  <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://stewarthill.co.uk/blogs/news"/>
  <link rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" href="https://stewarthill.co.uk/blogs/news.atom"/>
  <title>Stewart Hill  - Press</title>
  <updated>2019-08-08T17:44:00+01:00</updated>
  <author>
    <name>Stewart Hill </name>
  </author>
  <entry>
    <id>https://stewarthill.co.uk/blogs/news/daily-mail-the-battle-to-rebuild-our-family-major-stewart-hill-became-a-social-hand-grenade-after-a-taliban-bomb-tore-into-his-brain-now-he-and-his-award-winning-actress-daughter-liv-hill-tell-how-he-learned-to-be-her-daddy-again</id>
    <published>2019-08-08T17:44:00+01:00</published>
    <updated>2019-08-08T17:54:20+01:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://stewarthill.co.uk/blogs/news/daily-mail-the-battle-to-rebuild-our-family-major-stewart-hill-became-a-social-hand-grenade-after-a-taliban-bomb-tore-into-his-brain-now-he-and-his-award-winning-actress-daughter-liv-hill-tell-how-he-learned-to-be-her-daddy-again"/>
    <title>Daily Mail, &apos;The battle to rebuild our family: Major Stewart Hill became a &apos;social hand grenade&apos; after a Taliban bomb tore into his brain. Now he and his award-winning actress daughter Liv Hill tell how he learned to be her daddy again.&apos;</title>
    <author>
      <name>Stewart Hill</name>
    </author>
    <summary type="html">
      <![CDATA[<meta charset="utf-8"><span>By Richard Pendlebury for the Daily Mail Actress Liv Hill remembers ‘every vivid detail’ of the day a catastrophe changed her family’s life for ever. She had woken with the golden glow of a summer morning flooding her bedroom. For a while she lay and imagined that celestial figures were flitting about her bed. It was t...</span><p><a class="read-more" href="https://stewarthill.co.uk/blogs/news/daily-mail-the-battle-to-rebuild-our-family-major-stewart-hill-became-a-social-hand-grenade-after-a-taliban-bomb-tore-into-his-brain-now-he-and-his-award-winning-actress-daughter-liv-hill-tell-how-he-learned-to-be-her-daddy-again">More</a></p>]]>
    </summary>
    <content type="html">
      <![CDATA[<meta charset="utf-8">
<p><em>By Richard Pendlebury for the Daily Mail </em></p>
<meta charset="utf-8">
<p class="mol-para-with-font">Actress Liv Hill remembers ‘every vivid detail’ of the day a catastrophe changed her family’s life for ever.</p>
<p class="mol-para-with-font">She had woken with the golden glow of a summer morning flooding her bedroom. For a while she lay and imagined that celestial figures were flitting about her bed. It was the charming daydream of an artistic but introverted nine-year-old girl.</p>
<p class="mol-para-with-font">Eventually, she went downstairs to find her mother, Melissa. ‘I’ve been talking to the angels,’ she told her.</p>
<meta charset="utf-8">
<p class="mol-para-with-font"><img src="https://i.dailymail.co.uk/1s/2019/08/07/22/17017198-7334965-Stewart_Hill_was_left_without_his_memory_after_a_Taliban_bomb_wa-m-18_1565214660298.jpg" alt="Stewart Hill was left without his memory after a Taliban bomb was catapulted at his head during the Afghan war in 2009. Now in an exclusive interview, he discusses with his daughter how this became a turning point - and he has appeared in a West End play about Afghanistan, directed by Trevor Nunn"></p>
<meta charset="utf-8">
<p><strong>Stewart Hill was left without his memory after a Taliban bomb was catapulted at his head during the Afghan war in 2009. Now in an exclusive interview, he discusses with his daughter how this became a turning point - and he has appeared in a West End play about Afghanistan, directed by Trevor Nunn</strong></p>
<p>﻿The effect of this statement was unexpectedly traumatic. ‘Mum already looked unhappy but as soon as I said that she burst into tears,’ Liv recalls. ‘I had no idea why I had made her so upset. Of course she thought it meant that Daddy was dead.’</p>
<p class="mol-para-with-font">Unknown to Liv, there had been a knock on the door at 1am that same morning; a visitation that any family with a loved one serving in Afghanistan had come to dread.</p>
<p class="mol-para-with-font">On the step was an Army officer with devastating news. Liv’s father — Melissa’s husband — Major Stewart Hill, Officer Commanding B Company, 2nd Mercian, had suffered a serious head wound in Helmand the previous day. He was not expected to survive.</p>
<p class="mol-para-with-font">This summer marks the tenth anniversary of the bloodiest period of Britain’s most recent war in Afghanistan. In July and August 2009, 41 British soldiers were killed. Many more were wounded, often sustaining life-changing injuries.</p>
<p class="mol-para-with-font">The legacy of those wounds and the post-traumatic stress disorder suffered by thousands of veterans remains with us. But this is a story of how something rather wonderful and unexpected can emerge from a disaster.</p>
<meta charset="utf-8">
<p class="mol-para-with-font"><img src="https://i.dailymail.co.uk/1s/2019/08/07/22/17017188-7334965-In_the_ranks_He_spearheaded_the_Panther_s_Claw_ground_offensive_-m-19_1565214719627.jpg" alt="In the ranks: He spearheaded the 'Panther's Claw' ground offensive before his fatal injury. Here he lost many soldiers, includingÂ 18-year-old Private Robbie Laws and he has learnt to become 'content with who I am' over the years"></p>
<meta charset="utf-8">
<p class="mol-para-with-font"><strong>In the ranks: He spearheaded the 'Panther's Claw' ground offensive before his fatal injury. Here he lost many soldiers, including 18-year-old Private Robbie Laws and he has learnt to become 'content with who I am' over the years</strong></p>
<meta charset="utf-8">
<p class="mol-para-with-font">I have been privileged to witness the Hill family’s journey unfold over the course of the past decade. I was with Stewart when he was grievously wounded. I first met Liv four months later, at Sandringham House on the Queen’s Norfolk estate, when she was presented to the Prince of Wales, Colonel-in-Chief of the Mercian Regiment. Small and sombre, dressed in a smart winter coat, she was terribly shy.</p>
<p class="mol-para-with-font">‘I still am,’ she says.</p>
<p class="mol-para-with-font">Up to a point. She has become one of the most acclaimed British actors of her generation.</p>
<p class="mol-para-with-font">Aged 16 and in her first professional role, she was nominated for a BAFTA as one of the trio of leads in the BBC’s multi-award winning 2017 mini-series about the Rochdale child abuse scandal, Three Girls.</p>
<p class="mol-para-with-font">She received international festival awards for her debut feature film in 2018, Jellyfish, about a girl from a dysfunctional family who discovers a talent for stand-up comedy.</p>
<p class="mol-para-with-font">Now 19, this summer she has been starring at the Royal National Theatre in the critically garlanded revival of Caryl Churchill’s play Top Girls about a career-driven woman.</p>
<meta charset="utf-8">
<p class="mol-para-with-font"><img src="https://i.dailymail.co.uk/1s/2019/08/07/22/17017194-7334965-image-a-17_1565214243407.jpg" alt="His daughter Liv Hill (pictured far left) went on to play a lead in the BBC's multi-award winning 2017 mini-series about the Rochdale child abuse scandal Three Girls. Initially her parents had reservations about the series but changed their mind once they read the script and 'saw it was a story that needed to be told'"></p>
<meta charset="utf-8">
<p class="mol-para-with-font"><strong>His daughter Liv Hill (pictured far left) went on to play a lead in the BBC's multi-award winning 2017 mini-series about the Rochdale child abuse scandal Three Girls. Initially her parents had reservations about the series but changed their mind once they read the script and 'saw it was a story that needed to be told'</strong></p>
<meta charset="utf-8">
<div itemprop="articleBody" id="ext-gen46">
<p class="mol-para-with-font">And Liv will play double Oscar winner Glenda Jackson’s younger self in a BBC television adaptation of the novel Elizabeth Is Missing about dementia.</p>
<p class="mol-para-with-font">And her father?</p>
<p class="mol-para-with-font">He survived. Just. But as a different Stewart Hill from the man who led his men into battle on the morning of July 4, 2009.</p>
<p class="mol-para-with-font">We three met again recently around the kitchen table of the Hills’ home in a Derbyshire village.</p>
<p class="mol-para-with-font">Liv was back for a brief visit from London. She has never spoken about her family’s trauma and she later described our discussion as feeling like a ‘therapy session’. Often father and daughter were asking questions of each other.</p>
<p class="mol-para-with-font">Back in July 2009, Stewart had led a spearhead of the biggest British ground offensive of the Afghan war, codenamed ‘Panther’s Claw’.</p>
<p class="mol-para-with-font">His company was to push into an area near Babaji which had been controlled by the Taliban for the previous two years. The aim was to enable locals to vote in the national elections later that summer.</p>
<p class="mol-para-with-font">I was embedded with his unit, along with Mail photographer Jamie Wiseman. Stewart cut an impressive figure. Before the operation, he gathered his men and quoted Field Marshal Montgomery: ‘Decision in action, calmness in crisis.’</p>
<p class="mol-para-with-font">We spent the first night sleeping in a farmyard before moving to the ‘start line’ for the operation on the other side of an irrigation canal.</p>
<p class="mol-para-with-font">As the troops crossed the waterway, Wiseman took a photograph. This was later used by Stewart as the subject of one of his first paintings, which in turn inspired the Turner Prize-winning artist Grayson Perry to interpret it as a tapestry.</p>
<p class="mol-para-with-font">The Taliban response was swift. For the rest of a blazing hot day, the troops were hit by ambushes in the dense jungle and small agricultural fields of the ‘green zone’.</p>
<p class="mol-para-with-font">But it was not until the light began to fade that casualties occurred. First, an accompanying armoured vehicle was struck by a Taliban rocket. One of Stewart’s soldiers, 18-year-old Private Robbie Laws, was killed instantly.</p>
<p class="mol-para-with-font">The vehicle commander lost a leg. A medical evacuation helicopter was called to take the casualties. As Stewart and his company HQ group moved away from the landing zone, another soldier, Lance Corporal David Dennis, 29, of the Light Dragoons, stepped on an enormous improvised explosive device.</p>
<p class="mol-para-with-font">The explosion killed Dennis and wounded everyone else in the near vicinity, including Stewart. Two pieces of shrapnel entered his brain, causing irreparable damage.</p>
<p class="mol-para-with-font">As he hung between life and death in Afghanistan, his family and friends rallied round at home. Liv recalls being taken strawberry-picking for the day by a friend of her mother’s — a very English response to crisis.</p>
<p class="mol-para-with-font">Eventually, Stewart was evacuated to the military wing of a hospital in Birmingham. Though conscious, he had lost large areas of his memory. ‘I thought it was 2001 and Olivia was still 12 months old,’ he recalls.</p>
<p class="mol-para-with-font">‘I did not recognise her photograph when they showed it to me. I did not have a nine-year-old daughter as far as I was concerned.</p>
<p class="mol-para-with-font">‘Melissa would not allow Olivia to see me until my memory had returned sufficiently to recognise her in the picture.’</p>
<p class="mol-para-with-font">The first visit was testing for both father and child. ‘Dad smelled really 'gravelly,' ’ recalls Liv. ‘He still had sand and dust from Afghanistan on his hands. He looked really ill.’</p>
<p class="mol-para-with-font">She had been told his memory was bad ‘so I had a list of questions to ask him. The first was 'What is my name?' which he answered correctly. The second was “Who is Homer Simpson’s son?”</p>
<p class="mol-para-with-font">‘We had both loved the Simpsons and watched it together. But he couldn’t remember Bart and I thought, 'Oh my God, Daddy’s really sick.' That was a moment of shock!’</p>
<p class="mol-para-with-font">They both laugh at the absurdity of the exchange now.</p>
<p class="mol-para-with-font">Stewart was well enough to attend his battalion’s medal ceremony at Sandringham that November. But the long-term impairments caused by his head injury were apparent; memory and hearing loss, anger issues, imbalance and a sometimes embarrassing lack of restraint.</p>
<p class="mol-para-with-font">‘He has become a social hand grenade,’ Melissa told me at the time.</p>
<p class="mol-para-with-font">The next few years were very difficult for the Hill family as Stewart saw the life he had expected to lead fall away and struggled to cope. He felt abandoned by the military.</p>
<p class="mol-para-with-font">‘The worst week came the following May,’ he says. ‘I got a phone call to say I was selected for promotion to the rank of Lieutenant Colonel. I thought 'Yes! This is my career made, I am back on track.'</p>
<p class="mol-para-with-font">‘But that same week I went to Headley Court in Surrey [then the military rehabilitation centre] and saw my care worker.</p>
<p class="mol-para-with-font">‘They wanted me to do a presentation on my brain injury. The following morning I was lying crying on my bed because I did not know where to start. My injury was preventing me. And that was that as far as the Army was concerned.’</p>
<p class="mol-para-with-font">Liv asks him: ‘And how long did it take you for you to accept that?’</p>
<p class="mol-para-with-font">‘Oh, by 2012 when I was medically discharged. I wanted to be out by then,’ says her father.</p>
<p class="mol-para-with-font">‘Because you were angry at them?’ she continues.</p>
<p class="mol-para-with-font">‘Yes, because I was angry. My life was s***,’ says Stewart.</p>
<p class="mol-para-with-font">Liv tells him: ‘The times I remembered you before the injury were very happy times. I was a daddy’s girl growing up and you were often away and that made me sad. Then the dynamic changed. It did not help that when you got the injury you would get angry very quickly.</p>
<p class="mol-para-with-font">‘It was challenging. We butted heads. It became a testy relationship because of my age and because of your injury.’</p>
<p class="mol-para-with-font">She adds: ‘We still butt heads now, but I have so much respect for what you went through and the recovery. As a family we have learned to communicate.’</p>
<p class="mol-para-with-font">Stewart’s epiphany was the discovery of his creative abilities.</p>
<p class="mol-para-with-font">In recent years he has appeared in the West End in a play about Afghanistan, directed by Trevor Nunn. He is also a published poet and accomplished landscape and portrait painter. Actor Ray Winstone — whom he met while working on the play and who has supported him — and the Duke of Bedford are among an eclectic range of public figures he has put on canvas.</p>
<p class="mol-para-with-font">At the same time, his older daughter — he has an eight-year-old as well — found her own place in the arts world.</p>
<p class="mol-para-with-font">Aged 14, she began to attend the Nottingham Actors Studio. At 16, she had her first professional audition — for Three Girls.</p>
<p class="mol-para-with-font">‘I only went to gain some audition experience,’ she says. ‘All I knew was they wanted girls who were natural. The performance should be very understated and subtle. Whatever they saw in me was right for the character.’</p>
<p class="mol-para-with-font">After the second audition, she was told she had the part of Ruby, one of the three abused girls of the title role. At first, her parents had their reservations because of the subject matter and strong language the part demanded. ‘But we read the script several times and saw it was a story that needed to be told,’ says Stewart.</p>
<p class="mol-para-with-font">On set, she had to be accompanied by a chaperone because of her age. During filming, she met the girl she was portraying.</p>
<p class="mol-para-with-font">‘She talked about her own experiences as if she was making a cup of tea,’ says Liv. ‘It was so strange and awful it just seemed to have gone over her head.’</p>
<p class="mol-para-with-font">The role ‘took me completely out of my bubble from this lovely home in Derbyshire. It was very humbling.’ Three Girls won a host of awards and Liv got a BAFTA nomination for best supporting actress. She took her mum to the ceremony. Within a month of finishing the drama, she was filming the lead role in Jellyfish, which won her more rave reviews and prizes at the Edinburgh International Film Festival and a French film festival.</p>
<p class="mol-para-with-font">Then she played a serving girl opposite Charlotte Rampling in the film adaptation of Sarah Waters’s novel The Little Stranger.</p>
<p class="mol-para-with-font">That won her a London Critics’ Circle nomination for best young performer. Now she will appear opposite film and theatrical legend Glenda Jackson.</p>
<p class="mol-para-with-font">‘I feel incredibly lucky to be working alongside such experienced and talented actors, especially Glenda Jackson,’ she says.</p>
<p class="mol-para-with-font">Meanwhile, her father, 48, has achieved a kind of peace. ‘My improvement is through the arts,’ he says. ‘I am the living proof of the generation of new neural pathways. Every day is a little bit better.’</p>
<p class="mol-para-with-font">He has a new quote to live by. ‘Theodore Roosevelt said 'comparison is the thief of joy'. I had wasted so much energy comparing myself post injury to my old self, to others who were never injured and to those who have different kinds of injuries.</p>
<p class="mol-para-with-font">‘I have stopped doing that. I have to be content with who I have become.’</p>
<p class="mol-para-with-font">On the tenth anniversary ‘of the worst day of my life’, he visited Wendy Laws, the mother of Private Robbie Laws, whom he had not seen for several years.</p>
<p class="mol-para-with-font">‘I’m told that after I came out of the coma, I would ask how Robbie was and they would say 'he’s dead' and I would start to cry.</p>
<p class="mol-para-with-font">‘And the next day I would wake and ask the same question again and the same thing would happen. That went on for several days. I am proud that I cared for my soldiers.</p>
<p class="mol-para-with-font">‘In the last few months I have come to feel I am using the 'energies' that were lost by those soldiers who were killed that day.</p>
<p class="mol-para-with-font">‘I am using their energy. It would be a dishonour to them if I forgot that.’ </p>
<meta charset="utf-8">
<meta charset="utf-8">
<p class="mol-para-with-font"><a href="https://www.dailymail.co.uk/news/article-7334965/Actress-Liv-Hill-father-chat-dad-Afghan-war.html">https://www.dailymail.co.uk/news/article-7334965/Actress-Liv-Hill-father-chat-dad-Afghan-war.html</a></p>
</div>]]>
    </content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>https://stewarthill.co.uk/blogs/news/forces-network-invictus-artwork-former-personnel-showcase-creative-skills</id>
    <published>2019-07-24T18:00:00+01:00</published>
    <updated>2019-08-08T18:09:10+01:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://stewarthill.co.uk/blogs/news/forces-network-invictus-artwork-former-personnel-showcase-creative-skills"/>
    <title>Forces Network - Invictus Artwork: Former Personnel Showcase Creative Skills</title>
    <author>
      <name>Stewart Hill</name>
    </author>
    <summary type="html">
      <![CDATA[<meta charset="utf-8"><span>Alongside the sporting events, an art exhibition displaying artwork created by former servicemen is on full display. By Amy Wiltshire An art exhibition created by former Forces servicemen is on show in Sheffield. The gallery's showing is coinciding with the Invictus UK Trials taking place in the city throughout the wee...</span><p><a class="read-more" href="https://stewarthill.co.uk/blogs/news/forces-network-invictus-artwork-former-personnel-showcase-creative-skills">More</a></p>]]>
    </summary>
    <content type="html">
      <![CDATA[<meta charset="utf-8">
<div class="grid-x">
<div class="cell small-12 medium-10">
<p class="article-summary">Alongside the sporting events, an art exhibition displaying artwork created by former servicemen is on full display.</p>
</div>
</div>
<footer class="grid-x align-justify article-meta item-border item-border--top item-border--bottom item-border--small-hidden">
<div class="cell shrink">
<div class="entry-meta byline"><em>By Amy Wiltshire</em></div>
<div class="entry-meta byline"><em></em></div>
<div class="entry-meta byline"><em></em></div>
<div class="entry-meta byline"></div>
<div class="entry-meta byline"><iframe src="//players.brightcove.net/2685123856001/Hy7Zehglog_default/index.html?videoId=6063147185001" allowfullscreen="" frameborder="0"></iframe></div>
<div class="entry-meta byline"></div>
<div class="entry-meta byline"></div>
<div class="entry-meta byline">
<meta charset="utf-8">
<div class="rich-text paragraph paragraph--type--rich-text paragraph--view-mode--default">
<p>An art exhibition created by former Forces servicemen is on show in Sheffield.</p>
<p>The gallery's showing is coinciding with the Invictus UK Trials taking place in the city throughout the week.</p>
</div>
<div class="rich-text paragraph paragraph--type--rich-text paragraph--view-mode--default">
<p>'This Exhibition' showcases the work of six former soldiers who have turned to art to help them on their journey of rediscovery.</p>
<p>One of those men is Stewart Hill who described the difficulties he has faced since leaving the military.</p>
<p>He said: "I’ve really struggled with the loss of my Army career and what I perceived as my life. I’d lost my life.</p>
<p>"I really struggled psychologically and neurologically because of my brain impairments. I was just completely lost and was searching for things to improve my mind.</p>
<p>"I could not continue the thoughts and the horrible feelings that I had about me and wanting to end at times my life.</p>
<p>"To paint is so rewarding. Every time I put this brush down, it is positive energy that I am creating.</p>
<p>"That, for me, is just incredible. If I paint, I know I am in the absolute moment."</p>
</div>
<figure role="group" class="caption caption-article embedded-entity component-spacer">
<figure role="group" class="caption caption-article embedded-entity component-spacer">
<article class="media media-image view-mode-embedded" data-quickedit-entity-id="paragraph/198542" data-quickedit-entity-instance-id="0"><img src="https://www.forces.net/sites/default/files/styles/inline_image/public/Invictus%20Art%20Gallery%20Credit%20BFBS%2023072019.jpg?itok=CgGxiMz2" width="750" height="422" alt="Invictus Art Gallery Credit BFBS 23072019.jpg " typeof="foaf:Image" class="image-style-inline-image"></article>
<figcaption>People gathered to witness the art that has meant so much to the former soldiers.</figcaption>
<figcaption></figcaption>
<figcaption></figcaption>
</figure>
</figure>
<meta charset="utf-8">
<figure role="group" class="caption caption-article embedded-entity component-spacer">
<figcaption><a href="https://www.forces.net/news/invictus-artwork-former-servicemen-showcase-creative-skills">https://www.forces.net/news/invictus-artwork-former-servicemen-showcase-creative-skills</a></figcaption>
</figure>
<div class="paragraph paragraph--type--related-content paragraph--view-mode--default">
<div class="embedded-panel embedded-panel--standout">
<article class="card card--lead card--condensed teaser">
<div class="card-section">
<header><span class="card-category uppercase"><a href="https://www.forces.net/sport/invictus-games" hreflang="en"></a></span></header>
<header></header>
</div>
</article>
</div>
</div>
<div class="rich-text paragraph paragraph--type--rich-text paragraph--view-mode--default"></div>
</div>
<div class="entry-meta byline"><em></em></div>
<div class="entry-meta byline"><em></em></div>
<div class="entry-meta byline"><em></em></div>
</div>
</footer>]]>
    </content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>https://stewarthill.co.uk/blogs/news/evening-standard-art-by-injured-veterans-goes-on-show-in-first-world-war-centenary-exhibition</id>
    <published>2018-11-22T14:17:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2018-11-22T14:18:51+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://stewarthill.co.uk/blogs/news/evening-standard-art-by-injured-veterans-goes-on-show-in-first-world-war-centenary-exhibition"/>
    <title>Evening Standard - Art by injured veterans goes on show in First World War centenary exhibition</title>
    <author>
      <name>Stewart Hill</name>
    </author>
    <content type="html">
      <![CDATA[<meta charset="utf-8">
<p><img src="https://static.standard.co.uk/s3fs-public/thumbnails/image/2018/11/06/16/aftermath-veterans-art-0611b.jpeg?width=1000&amp;height=614&amp;fit=bounds&amp;format=pjpg&amp;auto=webp&amp;quality=70&amp;crop=16:9,offset-y0.5"></p>
<meta charset="utf-8">
<p>Work by the model<span> </span><a href="https://www.standard.co.uk/fashion/kate-moss-liam-payne-david-gandy-christmas-jumper-save-the-children-a3980466.html" class="body-link" data-vars-item-name="BL-3981616-https://www.standard.co.uk/fashion/kate-moss-liam-payne-david-gandy-christmas-jumper-save-the-children-a3980466.html" data-vars-event-id="c6">David Gandy</a><span> </span>will take centre stage in an exhibition featuring art by wounded veterans to coincide with the<span> </span><a href="https://www.standard.co.uk/news/london/the-best-pictures-of-tower-of-londons-stunning-armistice-memorial-lights-a3981516.html" class="body-link" data-vars-item-name="BL-3981616-https://www.standard.co.uk/news/london/the-best-pictures-of-tower-of-londons-stunning-armistice-memorial-lights-a3981516.html" data-vars-event-id="c6">Armistice centenary</a>. </p>
<p>Art In The Aftermath showcases paintings, photographs, poetry and films by soldiers injured in Bosnia, Iraq and Afghanistan. Many had not written or painted before, but turned to art and poetry to help overcome mental and physical injuries, including  post-traumatic stress disorder.</p>
<p>The exhibition, marking 100 years since the end of the First World War, has been organised by<span> </span><a href="https://www.standard.co.uk/topic/emma-willis" class="body-link" data-vars-item-name="BL-3981616-https://www.standard.co.uk/topic/emma-willis" data-vars-event-id="c6">Emma Willis</a>, a designer who started charity Style For Soldiers in 2008 after visiting wounded veterans returning from Afghanistan. She has worked with hundreds of injured men and women to create bespoke clothing for job interviews and other occasions.</p>
<p>Charity patron Gandy directed a film with veterans, while TV presenter<span> </span><a href="https://www.standard.co.uk/topic/nick-knowles" class="body-link" data-vars-item-name="BL-3981616-https://www.standard.co.uk/topic/nick-knowles" data-vars-event-id="c6">Nick Knowles</a><span> </span>and actor Ray Winstone sat as models for Lieutenant-Colonel Stewart Hill, who sustained a brain injury in a blast in Afghanistan. Actor Charles Dance featured in short film For Love Of Words by former bomb disposal expert and triple amputee Matt Weston.</p>
<p>Dance said: “My job as an actor is to pretend. I pretend to be a soldier, I pretend to fire a gun, I pretend to be brave, I pretend to be injured — so I have the greatest possible admiration and respect for our servicemen and women. Whatever help we lucky ones can give is the least we can do.”</p>]]>
    </content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>https://stewarthill.co.uk/blogs/news/as-featured-in-the-times</id>
    <published>2018-11-22T13:57:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2019-02-04T15:50:31+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://stewarthill.co.uk/blogs/news/as-featured-in-the-times"/>
    <title>The Times, &apos;Afghanistan veteran draws up plans for an art career.&apos;</title>
    <author>
      <name>Stewart Hill</name>
    </author>
    <summary type="html">
      <![CDATA[An army officer who suffered life changing injuries in Afghanistan is now gorging a new career as a portrait painter after art became part of his recovery.<p><a class="read-more" href="https://stewarthill.co.uk/blogs/news/as-featured-in-the-times">More</a></p>]]>
    </summary>
    <content type="html">
      <![CDATA[<meta charset="utf-8"><img src="https://stewarthill.co.uk/wp-content/uploads/2018/04/times-article.png">]]>
    </content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>https://stewarthill.co.uk/blogs/news/daily-mail-prince-william-launches-poetry-competition</id>
    <published>2018-02-02T09:04:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2019-02-05T09:05:10+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://stewarthill.co.uk/blogs/news/daily-mail-prince-william-launches-poetry-competition"/>
    <title>Daily Mail, &apos;Prince William launches poetry competition.&apos;</title>
    <author>
      <name>Stewart Hill</name>
    </author>
    <content type="html">
      <![CDATA[<meta charset="utf-8">
<p class="mol-para-with-font">Prince William<span> </span>launched a poetry competition yesterday to find a modern Wilfred Owen.</p>
<p class="mol-para-with-font">The contest, to mark the opening of a £300 million centre for wounded military personnel, is inspired by the likes of Owen, Siegfried Sassoon and Rupert Brooke and seeks work that reflects on ‘humankind’s ability to triumph over adversity’.</p>
<p class="mol-para-with-font">The winning entry will be chosen by the public and will be read by William at the Defence National Rehabilitation Centre at Stanford Hall near Loughborough later this year.</p>
<meta charset="utf-8">
<p class="mol-para-with-font"><img src="https://i.dailymail.co.uk/i/pix/2018/02/02/22/48D4F25200000578-0-image-m-4_1517609139493.jpg" alt="Prince William launched a poetry competition yesterday to find a modern Wilfred Owen. He will read the winning poem at the Defence National Rehabilitation Centre in London. Pictured is Prince William at the centre during the City Veterans third annual dinner in November"></p>
<meta charset="utf-8">
<p class="mol-para-with-font">To publicise the competition, Stewart Hill, a former Army officer badly injured in a roadside bomb attack in Afghanistan, read an abridged version of his poem, Identity, reproduced right, on Radio 4’s Today programme yesterday.</p>
<p class="mol-para-with-font">In July 2009, Lt Col Hill was blown into a hedge by the explosion. He still has two pieces of shrapnel in his brain.</p>
<p class="mol-para-with-font">To find out more and submit a poem, visit<span> </span><a target="_blank" class="" rel="nofollow noopener noreferrer" href="http://www.poemtoremember.co.uk/">www.poemtoremember.co.uk</a>.</p>]]>
    </content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>https://stewarthill.co.uk/blogs/news/bury-times-afghanistan-veteran-stewart-hills-sculpture-on-display-at-bury-art-museum</id>
    <published>2017-07-18T09:33:00+01:00</published>
    <updated>2019-02-05T09:34:11+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://stewarthill.co.uk/blogs/news/bury-times-afghanistan-veteran-stewart-hills-sculpture-on-display-at-bury-art-museum"/>
    <title>Bury Times, &apos;Afghanistan veteran Stewart Hill&apos;s sculpture on display at Bury Art Museum.&apos;</title>
    <author>
      <name>Stewart Hill</name>
    </author>
    <content type="html">
      <![CDATA[<meta charset="utf-8">
<div class="article-image-containter"><img src="https://www.burytimes.co.uk/resources/images/6598381.jpg?display=1&amp;htype=0&amp;type=responsive-gallery" alt="Stewart Hill with his sculpture, on show at Bury Art Museum"></div>
<p class="hero-caption"><span>Stewart Hill with his sculpture, on show at Bury Art Museum</span></p>
<meta charset="utf-8">
<p class="article-first-paragraph">A REMARKABLE sculpture made by a local military veteran has been delivered to Bury Art Museum to highlight the “life-changing”<span> </span>work<span> </span>of a group of service personnel from Greater Manchester.</p>
<p>It is part of an exhibition which has recently completed a two-week run at Salford’s prestigious Lowry Hotel.</p>
<p>Stewart Hill was part of a Royal British Legion project using art to aid recovery from complex post-conflict conditions.</p>
<p>His latest piece made of wire tackles tough memories from his past and will be on display at the museum, in Moss Street, until the end of September.</p>
<div id="inArticleAd-1" class="advert-container">
<div id="DFP_in_article_mpu" data-google-query-id="CLuJ2-ukpOACFVPk7Qod-bEKLw">
<div id="google_ads_iframe_/154725070/www.burytimes.co.uk/news_2__container__"><iframe frameborder="0" src="https://tpc.googlesyndication.com/safeframe/1-0-31/html/container.html" id="google_ads_iframe_/154725070/www.burytimes.co.uk/news_2" title="3rd party ad content" name="" scrolling="no" marginwidth="0" marginheight="0" width="300" height="250" data-is-safeframe="true" sandbox="allow-forms allow-pointer-lock allow-popups allow-popups-to-escape-sandbox allow-same-origin allow-scripts allow-top-navigation-by-user-activation" data-google-container-id="5" allowfullscreen="" webkitallowfullscreen="" mozallowfullscreen="" data-load-complete="true"></iframe></div>
</div>
</div>
<p>Mr Hill took up art after brain injuries caused by a shrapnel wound suffered in Afghanistan in 2009 caused him to retire from the Army, where he served as a Lieutenant Colonel.</p>
<p>Bravo 22 Company is the Royal British Legion's recovery through the arts programme for the Armed Forces community.</p>
<p>The 12 participants worked under the guidance of professional sculptor Al Johnson.</p>
<p>Ms Johnson said: “This has been a really exciting opportunity to take part in a creative project making life-size sculptures, and to then share these very personal pieces with the public at an exhibition at the Lowry Hotel.</p>
<div class="teads-adCall"></div>
<p>“It has been life-changing for some of them.</p>
<p>“Each of the sculptures is unique to its creator and tells a different story of recovery; from a painful memory to worries about civilian life or injuries that can’t be physically seen.”</p>
<p>The veterans, who have all been sourced by the Legion, had just four weeks to create their pieces.</p>
<p>Alison Bunn, Greater Manchester area manager for the Royal British Legion, said: “Through art, the project aims to improve participants’ self-awareness, confidence, self-esteem and motivation to help to move them along their individual recovery pathway.</p>
<p>“They are given a platform to express themselves, through art.</p>
<p>“This is just one of the ways we are using your donations to help support our Armed Forces community in Greater Manchester.”</p>
<div id="inArticleAd-2" class="advert-container">
<div id="DFP_in_article_2" data-google-query-id="CITN1uukpOACFQHj7QodKPoOqg">
<div id="google_ads_iframe_/154725070/www.burytimes.co.uk/news_3__container__"><iframe id="google_ads_iframe_/154725070/www.burytimes.co.uk/news_3" title="3rd party ad content" name="google_ads_iframe_/154725070/www.burytimes.co.uk/news_3" width="300" height="250" scrolling="no" marginwidth="0" marginheight="0" frameborder="0" srcdoc="" data-google-container-id="6" allowfullscreen="" webkitallowfullscreen="" mozallowfullscreen="" data-load-complete="true"></iframe></div>
</div>
</div>
<p>Actor Ray Winstone, patron of The Art of Recovery project, said: “Bravo 22 helps wounded, injured and sick Service personnel, along with veterans and family members, on their path of recovery through theatre or art.</p>
<p>“It’s an awesome project.”</p>
<p>As the nation’s largest Armed Forces charity, The Royal British Legion aims to help service personnel, veterans and their families live on to a more hopeful future and provide a voice for the Armed Forces community.</p>
<p class="hero-caption"><span> </span></p>]]>
    </content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>https://stewarthill.co.uk/blogs/news/from-army-to-artist-the-stewart-hill-q-a-speakers-corner</id>
    <published>2016-02-01T14:04:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2019-02-04T15:35:05+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://stewarthill.co.uk/blogs/news/from-army-to-artist-the-stewart-hill-q-a-speakers-corner"/>
    <title>From Army to Artist: The Stewart Hill Q&amp;A - Speakers Corner</title>
    <author>
      <name>Stewart Hill</name>
    </author>
    <content type="html">
      <![CDATA[<meta charset="utf-8"><meta charset="utf-8">
<p><img src="https://www.speakerscorner.co.uk/media/image/sh470.png" alt="From Army to Artist: The Stewart Hill Q&amp;A"></p>
<p> </p>
<p>In 2009 Stewart Hill suffered a traumatic brain injury during a second tour in Afghanistan. A Lieutenant Colonel, Stewart was blown into a ditch when one of his men stepped on an IED. He was found some distance away with his radio antennae embedded in his skull.</p>
<p>What followed was years of rehabilitation, not only for his physical injuries but mentally. Along with perforated eardrums and a loss of sense of smell and taste, Stewart's cognitive processes had been affected by the explosion making it difficult for him to process and organise information. </p>
<p>Despite this, Stewart made progress and is now able to share his story with corporate audiences as a speaker, speaking specifically on overcoming adversity, leadership, change and - of course - motivation. </p>
<p>We caught up with Stewart recently here...</p>
<p><strong>You talk very candidly about your injuries and the effect it had you and on those around you; the challenges with depression during your recovery. How long did it take mentally to get to where you are now?</strong></p>
<p>For the first year after my injury, I was positive about my recovery as I did not understand the impact of the brain injury on my life: do a few press ups, go for some runs, get fit again, and all would be well. I did not notice the problems with my brain until I experienced difficulties. If you're missing a leg, you know immediately you cannot walk, but there is nothing explicit if you're missing part of the brain.</p>
<p>My mood continued to drop the more I realised I could not match what I was able to do before - I was exhausted every time I used my brain. Reluctantly, I admitted to my therapist that I needed anti-depressants (the term depression was anathema to me), but I became more depressed over the next couple of years as I discovered more of my new limitations.</p>
<p>It was not until 2013/14, some 4-5 years later, that I began to improve my mood and my perceived quality of life.</p>
<p><img title="shstage.png" alt="shstage.png" width="900" height="534" align="middle" class=" lazyloaded" data-src="/media/image/shstage.png" src="https://www.speakerscorner.co.uk/media/image/shstage.png"></p>
<p><strong><span>Stewart recently speaking on stage about his experiences</span></strong></p>
<p><strong>You’ve said that you changed your views on depression from being a weakness (before the accident) and just being a case of ‘pulling yourself together’ to understanding it as a very real and personal issue. Having witnessed both viewpoints, what do you think the obstacles are to the stigma around depression being lifted?</strong></p>
<p>It’s as simple as the expectation that a ‘man’ should not be depressed. I was the strong one in my family, I had a role in protecting my family, could not be the one who was struggling mentally. Being in the military compounded this view; the culture that depression is a weakness and one should just ‘get a grip’. Dare I write it, but the main stigma is that it’s not manly to be depressed, it’s not what men do…supposedly.</p>
<p><strong>You also used good old-fashioned PMA to get through this. How did that work, given what you’d been through?</strong></p>
<p>I began painting and drawing again at the end of 2010 by a chance meeting with an artist (I had not drawn anything since ‘0’ Level art at school in 1986). I understood immediately painting and drawing allowed me to escape my very negative emotions, and began engaging with art when my mood was really low. Painting and drawing means one has to study any item objectively and consider it’s shape, tone and colour etc to recreate something; by looking closely at the object, I appreciated it’s beauty.</p>
<p><img title="shbuilding.png" alt="shbuilding.png" width="900" height="600" class=" lazyloaded" data-src="/media/image/shbuilding.png" src="https://www.speakerscorner.co.uk/media/image/shbuilding.png"></p>
<p><strong><span>Stewart visits the BBC's DIY SOS Homes for Veterans Project </span></strong></p>
<p>As my mood improved, I recognised I was responsible for my thoughts and began to understand the benefits of considering things differently. If I could create negative thoughts, why not create positive ones? Reading books on thinking positively (the type one sees in airport bookshelves I used to dismiss out of hand) intrigued me and, through effort and practice, I experienced the considerable benefits of positive thinking. My experiences in self-improvement now allow me to switch instantly to feeling good as soon as I recognise I have a negative thought.</p>
<p><strong>What are the main lesson(s) that you’ve learned from the last few years?</strong></p>
<p>The main lesson is that my suffering has been the catalyst for profound reflection and new possibilities.</p>
<p>I've also learned the importance of preserving the mind's energy - like any muscle the brain needs rest to grow. Resting the mind allows room for growth, thereby increasing one’s capacity, performance and life.</p>
<p>Living in the moment is the most efficient way to do this - it allows you to focus attention and deal with complexity one moment at a time. </p>
<p><img title="shph.png" alt="shph.png" width="798" height="533" align="middle" class=" lazyloaded" data-src="/media/image/shph.png" src="https://www.speakerscorner.co.uk/media/image/shph.png"></p>
<p><strong><span>Stewart with HRH Prince Harry</span></strong></p>
<p>Too often we mainly use one side of the brain when we should utilise both sides, right and left, to achieve true balance in our lives. Understand your brain to become a better leader. </p>
<p>Life and work are about people. In a world of process, we tend to forget about people. Employees account for the majority of costs on a balance sheet yet we don’t measure their worth. Leadership is about people. It’s a cliché because it’s true: ‘treat others as you would expect to be treated’ unless you’re a psychopath of course. Leaders are followed because they treat people with respect. Compassion and daily acts of kindness to oneself and others are enriching.</p>
<p><strong>What are your plans for the future?</strong></p>
<p>To become an accomplished artist, to show others how beautiful life can be (without me sounding like Mother Theresa), and to be the best I can. The most satisfying part of being an Officer was helping soldiers grow and reach their potential. I would eventually like to have a social enterprise or charity educating and teaching young people to realise their potential. Either that or become a Jedi Knight. </p>
<p><strong>The force is strong in you, Stewart, for sure. Any final thoughts?</strong></p>
<p>I would like people to see how beautiful life is without suffering trauma first.</p>
<p><strong><span><img title="Stewart Hill art" alt="shill-art.jpg" width="782" height="585" class=" lazyloaded" data-src="/media/image/shill-art.jpg" src="https://www.speakerscorner.co.uk/media/image/shill-art.jpg"></span></strong></p>
<p><strong><span>From army to artist: "If I could create negative thoughts, why not create positive ones?"</span></strong></p>
<p><span>If you would like to book Stewart or find out more about him, please call the office or enquiry form at the top of this page. Stewart's topics include:</span></p>
<p><span><a href="https://www.speakerscorner.co.uk/listing/motivational-speakers">Motivation</a>, <a href="https://www.speakerscorner.co.uk/listing/leadership-speakers">Leadership</a>, <a href="https://www.speakerscorner.co.uk/listing/teamwork-speakers">Teamwork</a>, and <a href="https://www.speakerscorner.co.uk/listing/change-and-turnaround-speakers">Change</a></span></p>]]>
    </content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>https://stewarthill.co.uk/blogs/news/the-mirror-stars-help-launch-christmas-appeal-for-walking-with-the-wounded</id>
    <published>2015-12-01T15:36:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2019-02-04T15:43:46+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://stewarthill.co.uk/blogs/news/the-mirror-stars-help-launch-christmas-appeal-for-walking-with-the-wounded"/>
    <title>The Mirror - &apos;Stars help launch Christmas appeal for Walking With the Wounded.&apos;</title>
    <author>
      <name>Stewart Hill</name>
    </author>
    <content type="html">
      <![CDATA[<meta charset="utf-8">
<p><span>Simon Cowell, Cheryl Fernandez-Versini and Rita Ora back this year's Mirror Christmas appeal Walking With the Wounded.</span></p>
<meta charset="utf-8">
<p><em><span class="author-label">By Rod McPhee</span></em></p>
<meta charset="utf-8">
<figure class="in-article-image lead-article-image" itemprop="image" itemscope="" itemtype="http://schema.org/ImageObject"><img srcset="https://i2-prod.mirror.co.uk/incoming/article6930253.ece/ALTERNATES/s508/WOUNDED.jpg 508w, https://i2-prod.mirror.co.uk/incoming/article6930253.ece/ALTERNATES/s810/WOUNDED.jpg 810w" src="https://i2-prod.mirror.co.uk/incoming/article6930253.ece/ALTERNATES/s615/WOUNDED.jpg" alt="Walking with the Wounded at the X Factor Studios" content="https://i2-prod.mirror.co.uk/incoming/article6930253.ece/ALTERNATES/s615/WOUNDED.jpg">
<figcaption><span class="caption" itemprop="description">Walking with the Wounded at the X Factor Studios</span><span class="credit" itemprop="author"><span> </span>(Image: Tom Dymond)</span></figcaption>
</figure>
<div class="article-body" itemprop="articleBody">
<form class="skinny-signup skinny-signup-top publication-theme-border publication-theme-background-with-transparency" data-mod="skinnySignup" data-json='{"mailingListId":"55334","displayName":"daily news","contentId":6314564,"endpointUrl":"https://comm-proxy.tm-awx.com/api/publications/mirror/subscriptions/"}' data-observed="false" data-init="true">
<span class="skinny-header"></span>
<div class="skinny-form"></div>
</form>
<p>When Cheryl Fernandez-Versini flew out to Afghanistan with the Mirror four years ago, she saw firsthand the courage of our forces and the vital work they were doing in the war-torn country.</p>
<p>That’s why she and the other X Factor judges are helping launch this year’s Daily Mirror Christmas appeal for ex-servicemen and women whose struggles continue long after they’ve left the battlefield.</p>
<p>We’re teaming up with military charity Walking With The Wounded to help those with physical injuries, mental health issues such as post-traumatic stress disorder, and problems re-adjusting to civilian life.</p>
<p>The<span> </span><a data-action="walking-with-the-wounded" data-content-type="section-topic" data-track="false" data-type="inline" data-word-count="4" href="http://www.mirror.co.uk/all-about/walking-with-the-wounded">Walking Home For Christmas</a><span> </span>initiative aims to throw a lifeline to the heroes who fight in war zones including Iraq and Afghanistan, but end up out of work or even homeless after returning to the UK.</p>
<figure class="in-article-image" data-mod="image" itemprop="image" itemscope="" itemtype="http://schema.org/ImageObject" data-observed="false" data-init="true">
<div class="outer">
<div class="spacer"></div>
<div class="mod-image"><img alt="" content="https://i2-prod.mirror.co.uk/incoming/article6930235.ece/ALTERNATES/s615b/Walking-with-the-Wounded-at-the-X-Factor-Studios.jpg" src="https://i2-prod.mirror.co.uk/incoming/article6930235.ece/ALTERNATES/s615b/Walking-with-the-Wounded-at-the-X-Factor-Studios.jpg"></div>
</div>
<figcaption><span class="caption" itemprop="description">Walking with the Wounded at the X Factor Studios</span><span> </span><span class="credit" itemprop="author">(Image: Tom Dymond)</span></figcaption>
</figure>
<p>So put your best foot forward, get walking over the festive period – and help raise much-needed funds for the charity. Backing our appeal, Cheryl says: “I saw at first hand the work the servicemen do when I went out to Afghanistan a few years ago. I was humbled by everyone I met there.</p>
<p>“<a data-action="mirror-christmas-appeal" data-content-type="section-topic" data-track="false" data-type="inline" data-word-count="6" href="http://www.mirror.co.uk/all-about/mirror-christmas-appeal">The Walking Home For Christmas campaign</a><span> </span>is a brilliant way for families to get behind our armed forces during the festive season. These men and women who fight for our country are so brave and they deserve all the support we can give.”</p>
<div id="perform-placeholder" class="placeholder" data-config='{"name":"perform-placeholder","componentType":"placeholder","referenceNode":".article-body &gt; p:nth-of-type(6)","type":"performPlaceholder","relativePos":"after"}' data-placeholder-placeholder="" data-response-start="1949.0000000223517" data-type="placeholder" style="background: transparent; border: 0px; font-size: 16px; margin: 0px; outline: 0px; padding: 0px; vertical-align: baseline;">Simon Cowell adds: “This is obviously a really important campaign helping people who have faced hardship and homelessness get their lives back on track. It’s really easy for everyone to get involved. Just put on your walking boots and support the Mirror’s Walking Home For Christmas campaign.”</div>
<figure class="in-article-image" data-mod="image" itemprop="image" itemscope="" itemtype="http://schema.org/ImageObject" data-observed="false" data-init="true">
<div class="outer">
<div class="spacer"></div>
<div class="mod-image"><img alt="" content="https://i2-prod.mirror.co.uk/incoming/article6930236.ece/ALTERNATES/s615b/Walking-with-the-Wounded-at-the-X-Factor-Studios.jpg" src="https://i2-prod.mirror.co.uk/incoming/article6930236.ece/ALTERNATES/s615b/Walking-with-the-Wounded-at-the-X-Factor-Studios.jpg"></div>
</div>
<figcaption><span class="caption" itemprop="description">Walking with the Wounded at the X Factor Studios</span><span> </span><span class="credit" itemprop="author">(Image: Tom Dymond)</span></figcaption>
</figure>
<p>Echoing the call, Rita Ora says: “So many servicemen and women need help after their time in the armed forces, and the work that Walking With The Wounded do to get them back on their feet is inspirational.</p>
<p>“I hope everyone gets behind this campaign and raises lots of money through their walks to show these servicemen how grateful we are for their sacrifice.”</p>
<p>And Nick Grimshaw says: “The Mirror’s Walking Home For Christmas fundraising campaign is a great way to raise much-needed money for an amazing charity that helps soldiers in need get their lives back on track. At Christmas especially, it’s the perfect time to pull together a group of your friends and family and organise a walk to show how grateful we all are for the servicemen and women who have dedicated their lives to our safety.”</p>
<p>On Saturday, the judges, contestants, hosts and guest Liv Tyler gave VIP treatment to three ex-servicemen visiting the hit ITV show.</p>
<figure class="in-article-image" data-mod="image" itemprop="image" itemscope="" itemtype="http://schema.org/ImageObject" data-observed="false" data-init="true">
<div class="outer">
<div class="spacer"></div>
<div class="mod-image"><img alt="" content="https://i2-prod.mirror.co.uk/incoming/article6930242.ece/ALTERNATES/s615b/Walking-with-the-Wounded-at-the-X-Factor-Studios.jpg" src="https://i2-prod.mirror.co.uk/incoming/article6930242.ece/ALTERNATES/s615b/Walking-with-the-Wounded-at-the-X-Factor-Studios.jpg"></div>
</div>
<figcaption><span class="caption" itemprop="description">Walking with the Wounded at the X Factor Studios</span><span> </span><span class="credit" itemprop="author">(Image: Tom Dymond)</span></figcaption>
</figure>
<p>They included ex-Army officer Stewart Hill, who has two pieces of shrapnel lodged a millimetre from his brain stem after an ambush in Afghanistan in 2009.</p>
<p>The injury means the married father of two struggles to make decisions and do basic tasks. “My wife Melissa has been head of the family because I can’t be relied upon to follow a task like remembering to pick up the kids,” says Stewart.</p>
<p>“For the first couple of years I found it incredibly upsetting and I was diagnosed with depression.</p>
<p>“I also found it difficult to work, even for one day, because it was so exhausting that I would be completely useless as a father or a husband.” Unable to do a full-time job, Stewart, of Draycott, Derbyshire, splits his time between a new career as an artist and raising awareness of “unseen” injuries servicemen and women suffer.</p>
<p>He’s been helped by art therapy sessions, paid for by Walking With The Wounded. Stewart, 44, says: “Art helps me see the world differently and focus on the positive. This is the first year I’ve been able to say I’m content and happy with who I am.”</p>
<p>And earlier this year, he did Walking With The Wounded’s Walk of Britain – one of their many expeditions funded by corporate sponsors to raise awareness of the charity’s work – with Prince Harry and Royal Marine Alec Robotham.</p>
<p>Alec, 29, was injured in Afghanistan when a suicide bomber detonated a bomb four feet behind him in 2010.</p>
<p>The communications equipment on his back saved his life, but he has struggled with his injuries. Alec, of Lovedean, Hants, says: “I’ve got a metal plate in my left foot, a very complicated right leg injury, nerve damage in my right arm and hearing loss. I was in a wheelchair for six months and on crutches for six months. I had to learn to walk again.</p>
<p>“I ruptured a lot of veins inside my leg so I’ve had a few cases of deep vein thrombosis, and I had a thin layer of skin graft on my knee all the way down. As a result, I got septicaemia a couple of times and nearly died from that.”</p>
<p>Now, after life-changing surgery, Alec is working with disaster relief organisation Team Rubicon, as well as continuing to help Walking With The Wounded.</p>
<p>He says: “They’ve taken a huge skin flap from my stomach to put on my leg. Now, it doesn’t stop me living my life. And I have the chance to think about what I really want to do and how I can help others, as I feel I have a lot to give.”</p>
<p>Walking Home For Christmas is specifically aimed at raising money for the charity’s Home Straight programme, helping veterans back into work and on their feet after finding themselves homeless or struggling to re-adjust to civilian life. Many had mental health issues.</p>
<div class="image-gallery-placeholder" data-gallery-id="6930249">
<div class="content">
<figure itemscope="" itemtype="http://schema.org/ImageObject">
<div class="outer">
<div class="mod-image" data-mod="image" data-observed="false" data-init="true"><a class="gallery-interaction" href="https://www.mirror.co.uk/incoming/gallery/walking-wounded-x-factor-studios-6930249"><img alt="" itemprop="image" content="https://www.mirror.co.uk/incoming/gallery/walking-wounded-x-factor-studios-6930249" data-height="409" data-width="615" src="https://i2-prod.mirror.co.uk/incoming/article6930253.ece/ALTERNATES/s615/WOUNDED.jpg"></a></div>
</div>
</figure>
<div class="call-to-action publication-font">
<figure class="mod-image blur" data-mod="image" data-observed="false" data-init="true"><a class="gallery-interaction" href="https://www.mirror.co.uk/incoming/gallery/walking-wounded-x-factor-studios-6930249"><img data-height="409" data-width="615" src="https://i2-prod.mirror.co.uk/incoming/article6930253.ece/ALTERNATES/s615/WOUNDED.jpg"></a></figure>
</div>
</div>
</div>
<p>Pat Barraclough, 55, of Sunderland, was one of those who found himself needing help after 22 years in the Royal Navy, including fighting in the Falklands, Sierra Leone and the Gulf War.</p>
<p>He says: “Some of the stuff I saw was harrowing and I still have flashbacks. At first that meant I had depression, I wanted to isolate myself from the world and I didn’t want to talk to anyone.</p>
<figure class="in-article-image" data-mod="image" itemprop="image" itemscope="" itemtype="http://schema.org/ImageObject" data-observed="false" data-init="true">
<div class="outer">
<div class="spacer"></div>
<div class="mod-image"><img alt="" content="https://i2-prod.mirror.co.uk/incoming/article6930239.ece/ALTERNATES/s615b/Pat-Barraclough.jpg" src="https://i2-prod.mirror.co.uk/incoming/article6930239.ece/ALTERNATES/s615b/Pat-Barraclough.jpg"></div>
</div>
<figcaption><span class="caption" itemprop="description">Pat Barraclough</span><span> </span><span class="credit" itemprop="author">(Image: Daily Mirror)</span></figcaption>
</figure>
<p>“That happened just at the time when I had to get out there and talk to people, to adjust to my new life and get a job. The trouble is, civilian life is so different to military life. I joined the navy at 16, so I’ve never had to go to a Jobcentre.”</p>
<p>And he hadn’t needed to deal with simple tasks like filling out paperwork.</p>
<p>Pat adds: “I was proud, so it took me a long time to ask for help, but because I did I’m a much more confident person now. Talking to people through Walking With The Wounded and other organisations changed my life for the better.</p>
<p>“We need to look after veterans. Now it’s up to the country to help them get on the straight and narrow.”</p>
</div>]]>
    </content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>https://stewarthill.co.uk/blogs/news/itv-news-walking-with-the-wounded-soldiers-receive-warm-welcome-in-draycott-village</id>
    <published>2015-10-17T09:02:00+01:00</published>
    <updated>2019-02-05T09:03:13+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://stewarthill.co.uk/blogs/news/itv-news-walking-with-the-wounded-soldiers-receive-warm-welcome-in-draycott-village"/>
    <title>ITV News, &apos;Walking with the Wounded soldiers receive warm welcome in Draycott village.&apos;</title>
    <author>
      <name>Stewart Hill</name>
    </author>
    <content type="html">
      <![CDATA[<meta charset="utf-8">
<figure class="item__content-block item__content-block--with-caption
                 item__content-block--image">
<div class="fluid-media-wrapper">
<div class="fluid-media-wrapper__media"><span class=" responsive-image" data-alt="Draycott villagers in Derbyshire give warm welcome to the soldiers " data-height="null" data-picture="true" data-width="null"><span data-src="https://news.images.itv.com/image/file/797578/stream_img.jpg" data-media="(min-width: 321px)"><img alt="Draycott villagers in Derbyshire give warm welcome to the soldiers " src="https://news.images.itv.com/image/file/797578/stream_img.jpg"></span></span></div>
</div>
<figcaption class="item__content-block__media-info">Draycott villagers in Derbyshire give warm welcome to the soldiers<span> </span><cite>Credit: ITV News Central</cite></figcaption>
</figure>
<div class="item__content-block item__content-block--markdown">
<p>The six Walking with the Wounded soldiers who are walking the length of Britain are stopping in Draycott in Derbyshire today.</p>
<p>They are walking to raise money for the Walking With the Wounded charity, of which Prince Harry is a patron.</p>
</div>
<figure class="item__content-block item__content-block--with-caption
                 item__content-block--image">
<div class="fluid-media-wrapper">
<div class="fluid-media-wrapper__media"><span class=" responsive-image" data-alt=" Lt Col Stewart Hill, from Draycott walking with the other soldiers. " data-height="null" data-picture="true" data-width="null"><span data-src="https://news.images.itv.com/image/file/797585/article_update_img.jpg"></span><span data-src="https://news.images.itv.com/image/file/797585/stream_img.jpg" data-media="(min-width: 321px)"><img alt=" Lt Col Stewart Hill, from Draycott walking with the other soldiers. " src="https://news.images.itv.com/image/file/797585/stream_img.jpg"></span></span></div>
</div>
<figcaption class="item__content-block__media-info">Lt Col Stewart Hill, from Draycott walking with the other soldiers.<span> </span><cite>Credit: ITV News Central</cite></figcaption>
</figure>
<div class="item__content-block item__content-block--markdown">
<p>One of the soldiers, Lt Col Stewart Hill, is from Draycott. He suffered a traumatic brain injury in Afghanistan in July 2009.</p>
<p>Stewart told his colleagues that he will get the best reception of all four Brits when they visit their homes. The village say they're determined not to let him down and today hundreds turned out to greet them.</p>
<p>The Draycott Village Fund said they decked the village out with lots of Union Flags and gave out more hand flags as the soldiers walk down the streets.</p>
</div>
<figure class="item__content-block item__content-block--with-caption
                 item__content-block--image">
<div class="fluid-media-wrapper">
<div class="fluid-media-wrapper__media"><span class=" responsive-image" data-alt="Local bands escort the soldiers through the route. " data-height="null" data-picture="true" data-width="null"><span data-src="https://news.images.itv.com/image/file/797582/article_update_img.jpg"></span><span data-src="https://news.images.itv.com/image/file/797582/stream_img.jpg" data-media="(min-width: 321px)"><img alt="Local bands escort the soldiers through the route. " src="https://news.images.itv.com/image/file/797582/stream_img.jpg"></span></span></div>
</div>
<figcaption class="item__content-block__media-info">Local bands escort the soldiers through the route.<span> </span><cite>Credit: ITV News Central</cite></figcaption>
</figure>
<div class="item__content-block item__content-block--markdown">
<p>Local bands, drummers and pipers turned up to welcome the six soldiers along the route.</p>
<p>The walk started in Edinburgh and ends in November, at Buckingham Palace. The route includes the home towns or villages of each of the four British Soldiers.</p>
<p>You can find out more about the charity<span> </span><a href="http://www.walkingwiththewounded.org.uk/" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">here</a>.</p>
</div>
<div class="item__content-block"><time datetime="2015-11-02" pubdate="" class="update__time-edited">Last updated Mon 2 Nov 2015</time></div>
<section class="update-story update-story--with-image">
<div class="columns"></div>
</section>]]>
    </content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>https://stewarthill.co.uk/blogs/news/daily-mail-marching-into-the-jaws-of-death-haunting-mail-photo-of-troops-launching-doomed-afghan-assault-thats-inspired-two-works-of-art</id>
    <published>2015-07-16T15:30:00+01:00</published>
    <updated>2019-02-04T15:30:56+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://stewarthill.co.uk/blogs/news/daily-mail-marching-into-the-jaws-of-death-haunting-mail-photo-of-troops-launching-doomed-afghan-assault-thats-inspired-two-works-of-art"/>
    <title>Daily Mail, &apos;Marching into the jaws of death: Haunting Mail photo of troops launching doomed Afghan assault that&apos;s inspired two works of art.&apos;</title>
    <author>
      <name>Stewart Hill</name>
    </author>
    <content type="html">
      <![CDATA[<meta charset="utf-8">
<p class="mol-para-with-font"><span>At 9.26am Afghan time on July 4, 2009, when most people back home were still safely abed, Mail staff photographer Jamie Wiseman took a picture which was to have an unexpected and remarkable legacy.</span></p>
<p class="mol-para-with-font"><span>In itself, the photograph was quite straightforward. It showed the infantry and armoured vehicles of the Light Dragoons Battle Group crossing the Nahr-e-Bagra canal near Babaji in Helmand province.</span></p>
<p class="mol-para-with-font"><span>They were the spearhead for the main thrust of Operation Panther’s Claw; Britain’s biggest ground offensive of the Afghan campaign. I was there to bear witness that day.</span></p>
<div class="mol-img-group xwArtSplitter">
<div class="mol-img">
<div class="image-wrap fff-pic">
<img id="i-d41dc73b36769bb9" src="https://i.dailymail.co.uk/i/pix/2015/07/17/07/2A98967A00000578-3164484-At_9_26am_Afghan_time_on_July_4_2009_when_most_people_back_home_-a-5_1437114903756.jpg" height="578" width="962" alt="At 9.26am Afghan time on July 4, 2009, when most people back home were still safely abed, Mail staff photographer Jamie Wiseman took a picture which was to have an unexpected and remarkable legacy. In itself, the photograph was quite straightforward. It showed the infantry and armoured vehicles of the Light Dragoons Battle Group crossing the Nahr-e-Bagra canal near Babaji in Helmand province..." class="blkBorder img-share b-loaded">
<div class="overlay-icon mobile-gallery">
<div class="mobile-gallery-icon"></div>
</div>
</div>
</div>
<p class="imageCaption">At 9.26am Afghan time on July 4, 2009, when most people back home were still safely abed, Mail staff photographer Jamie Wiseman took a picture which was to have an unexpected and remarkable legacy. In itself, the photograph was quite straightforward. It showed the infantry and armoured vehicles of the Light Dragoons Battle Group crossing the Nahr-e-Bagra canal near Babaji in Helmand province...</p>
</div>
<div class="mol-img-group xwArtSplitter mol-hidden-caption">
<div class="mol-img">
<div class="image-wrap fff-pic">
<img id="i-4bac932f164d8ca" src="https://i.dailymail.co.uk/i/pix/2015/07/17/07/2A988C4400000578-3164484-image-a-6_1437114903763.jpg" height="363" width="962" alt="" class="blkBorder img-share b-loaded">
<div class="overlay-icon mobile-gallery">
<div class="mobile-gallery-icon"></div>
</div>
</div>
</div>
</div>
<p class="mol-para-with-font"><span>The infantry were led by Major Stewart Hill, Officer Commanding of B Company, 2 Mercian. The Dragoons’ armoured troop was under the command of 27-year-old Lieutenant Guy Disney, who was a talented amateur jump jockey.</span></p>
<p class="mol-para-with-font"><span>What neither the photographer nor the men he recorded could know was the impending catastrophe.</span></p>
<p class="mol-para-with-font"><span>Within an hour of the picture being taken the British advance would experience its first ambush. For the rest of the day they were fiercely engaged by Taliban insurgents. That was to be expected.</span></p>
<p class="mol-para-with-font"><span>But by early evening, an extraordinary series of mischances had led to the command and control of the British battle group being effectively wiped out. Three men died, many more were wounded or in need of evacuation for heat stroke or shock.</span></p>
<p class="mol-para-with-font"><span>The careers of Hill and Disney were ended by the horrific injuries they suffered close to the canal. Others, while relatively unmarked, would never be the same as they were before they crossed the ‘start line’ that morning under Jamie Wiseman’s lens.</span></p>
<p class="mol-para-with-font"><span>July 2009 proved to be the bloodiest month of all in Britain’s 12-year Afghan combat operation, which ended last year. Between July 4 and 8, 2009, the Light Dragoons Battle Group alone suffered 66 casualties. </span></p>
<p class="mol-para-with-font"><span>That figure could not be reported at the time. Wiseman’s picture — when seen with the knowledge of what was about to happen to the advancing men — captured something profound about the UK’s role in Afghanistan and the futility of much of the sacrifice.</span></p>
<p class="mol-para-with-font"><span>Which is why this haunting image has provided the inspiration for two separate works of art exhibited at major London galleries.</span></p>
<div class="mol-img-group xwArtSplitter">
<div class="mol-img">
<div class="image-wrap fff-pic">
<img id="i-cff2e87b915c83d6" src="https://i.dailymail.co.uk/i/pix/2015/07/17/07/2A943D3000000578-3164484-Stewart_Hill_painted_the_above_picture_himself_It_is_based_direc-a-4_1437114903753.jpg" height="879" width="962" alt="Stewart Hill painted the above picture himself. It is based directly on Wiseman’s photo, and is on show at the Mall Galleries in Central London. Hill called it Lines Of Departure — which inspired the same title for Grayson Perry’s work — and in it he crystallises the eerie, pregnant calm before the lives of all involved were changed for ever" class="blkBorder img-share b-loaded">
<div class="overlay-icon mobile-gallery">
<div class="mobile-gallery-icon"></div>
</div>
</div>
</div>
<p class="imageCaption">Stewart Hill painted the above picture himself. It is based directly on Wiseman’s photo, and is on show at the Mall Galleries in Central London. Hill called it Lines Of Departure — which inspired the same title for Grayson Perry’s work — and in it he crystallises the eerie, pregnant calm before the lives of all involved were changed for ever</p>
</div>
<p class="mol-para-with-font"><span>The first to be shown, hung at the National Portrait Gallery earlier this year, was a large tapestry by the flamboyant artist Grayson Perry.</span></p>
<p class="mol-para-with-font"><span>It depicts Stewart Hill and two other soldiers who were also badly wounded in Afghanistan returning across the canal at the spot shown in the Wiseman photograph. The second, painted by Stewart Hill himself, is based directly on Wiseman’s photo, and is on show at the Mall Galleries in Central London.</span></p>
<p class="mol-para-with-font"><span>Hill called it Lines Of Departure — which inspired the same title for Grayson Perry’s work — and in it he crystallises the eerie, pregnant calm before the lives of all involved were changed for ever.</span></p>
<p class="mol-para-with-font"><span>Calamity struck as the British advanced into the enemy-held zone of small, tree-lined fields.</span></p>
<div class="mol-img-group xwArtSplitter">
<div class="mol-img">
<div class="image-wrap fff-pic">
<img id="i-3e9544112b88c7ec" src="https://i.dailymail.co.uk/i/pix/2015/07/17/07/2A943DBB00000578-3164484-This_large_tapestry_by_the_flamboyant_artist_Grayson_Perry_was_h-a-2_1437114903718.jpg" height="480" width="962" alt="This large tapestry, by the flamboyant artist Grayson Perry, was hung at the National Portrait Gallery earlier this year. It depicts Hill and two other soldiers who were also badly wounded in Afghanistan returning across the canal at the spot shown in the Wiseman photograph" class="blkBorder img-share b-loaded">
<div class="overlay-icon mobile-gallery">
<div class="mobile-gallery-icon"></div>
</div>
</div>
</div>
<p class="imageCaption">This large tapestry, by the flamboyant artist Grayson Perry, was hung at the National Portrait Gallery earlier this year. It depicts Hill and two other soldiers who were also badly wounded in Afghanistan returning across the canal at the spot shown in the Wiseman photograph</p>
</div>
<p class="mol-para-with-font"><span>First, a Taliban rocket-propelled grenade struck Disney’s command vehicle. The resulting explosion took off the young man’s right leg below the knee. Crouched in a nearby copse with 6 Platoon, 2 Mercian, I heard Disney report the fact over the radio, quite calmly. No more steeplechasing for him.</span></p>
<p class="mol-para-with-font"><span>The rocket strike also killed 18-year-old Private Robbie Laws, who was sitting inside Disney’s vehicle, while wounding Laws’ best friend Private Dan Eaglesfield. He was the same age, and the pair had been through training together.</span></p>
<p class="mol-para-with-font"><span>Before the advance, Eaglesfield had told me: ‘I wasn’t very good at school so I joined the Army. Me mum was furious I was coming here.’ Sensible mum. The boys’ story was told on the front page of this newspaper later that week.</span></p>
<p class="mol-para-with-font"><span>Under fire, the casualties were tended to by their comrades in the battle group before being evacuated by helicopter. But as Major Hill and his support staff walked away from the landing spot, one of them, Lance Corporal David Dennis, of the Light Dragoons, stepped on a large improvised explosive device.</span></p>
<p class="mol-para-with-font"><span>The enormous blast killed Dennis outright, sent shrapnel into Stewart Hill’s brain, and incapacitated the senior NCO, Company Sergeant Major Paul Muckle, and the attached Special Forces’ Forward Air Controller, whose job was to call in air strikes supporting the advance.</span></p>
<div class="mol-img-group xwArtSplitter">
<div class="third first">
<div class="mol-img">
<div class="image-wrap fff-pic"><img id="i-5474dd9147011962" src="https://i.dailymail.co.uk/i/pix/2015/07/17/07/05A6C251000005DC-3164484-Before_the_advance_Eaglesfield_left_said_I_wasn_t_very_good_at_s-a-3_1437114903750.jpg" height="446" width="308" alt="Before the advance, Eaglesfield (left) said: ‘I wasn’t very good at school so I joined the Army. Me mum was furious I was coming here’" class="blkBorder img-share b-loaded"></div>
<div class="container-3zJLP vertical-2XJd5"></div>
</div>
</div>
<div class="third">
<div class="mol-img">
<div class="image-wrap fff-pic"><img id="i-b9515493af6787e9" src="https://i.dailymail.co.uk/i/pix/2015/07/17/07/059A1AB1000005DC-3164484-Jem_McIlveen_who_commanded_Hill_s_6_Platoon_did_a_second_tour_of-a-1_1437114903683.jpg" height="446" width="308" alt="Jem McIlveen, who commanded Hill’s 6 Platoon, did a second tour of Afghanistan before leaving the Army in December 2013" class="blkBorder img-share b-loaded"></div>
<div class="container-3zJLP vertical-2XJd5"></div>
</div>
</div>
<div class="third">
<div class="mol-img">
<div class="image-wrap fff-pic">
<img id="i-bdde8588a7daaee7" src="https://i.dailymail.co.uk/i/pix/2015/07/17/07/059A2EF0000005DC-3164484-Stewart_Hill_was_not_expected_to_live_after_the_ambush-a-7_1437114903817.jpg" height="446" width="308" alt="Stewart Hill was not expected to live after the ambush" class="blkBorder img-share b-loaded">
<div class="overlay-icon mobile-gallery"><span> </span></div>
</div>
</div>
</div>
<p class="imageCaption">Before the advance, Eaglesfield (left) said: ‘I wasn’t very good at school so I joined the Army. Me mum was furious I was coming here.’ Jem McIlveen (centre), who commanded Hill’s 6 Platoon, did a second tour of Afghanistan before leaving the Army in December 2013. He has recently married and works for Goldman Sachs in the City. He was at the gallery’s private viewing this week to support Stewart Hill. Stewart Hill (right) was not expected to live after the ambush, following which he was flown to the UK in a medically induced coma</p>
</div>
<div class="mol-img-group floatXWHalfRHS">
<div class="mol-img">
<div class="image-wrap fff-pic"><img id="i-f7a6174d6c28af0d" src="https://i.dailymail.co.uk/i/pix/2015/07/17/07/2A943D9C00000578-3164484-Stewart_Hill_above_has_become_a_motivational_speaker_giving_talk-a-8_1437114903871.jpg" height="638" width="470" alt="Stewart Hill (above) has become a motivational speaker, giving talks to audiences as varied as the executives at the aeronautics firm Lockheed Martin and schoolchildren across the UK. What is surprising is his flourishing in the art world." class="blkBorder img-share b-loaded"></div>
</div>
<p class="imageCaption">Stewart Hill (above) has become a motivational speaker, giving talks to audiences as varied as the executives at the aeronautics firm Lockheed Martin and schoolchildren across the UK. What is surprising is his flourishing in the art world.</p>
</div>
<p class="mol-para-with-font"><span>Hill was not expected to live. That night he was flown to the UK in a medically induced coma and operated upon. Two pieces of metal were too close to his brain stem to remove safely. They are there to this day.</span></p>
<p class="mol-para-with-font"><span>The neurological side-effects of his severe injuries derailed what had promised to be a high-flying staff career, and he was eventually discharged as medically unfit to serve. He has not been impressed by the way the Army handled his recovery — but that is another story.</span></p>
<p class="mol-para-with-font"><span>Hill had to take a different path, and it has proved to be one few could have imagined. He has become a motivational speaker, giving talks to audiences as varied as the executives at the aeronautics firm Lockheed Martin and schoolchildren across the UK. What is surprising is his flourishing in the art world.</span></p>
<p class="mol-para-with-font"><span>First he appeared as an actor, playing someone like himself, in a touring production about Afghanistan’s military toll. It debuted to some acclaim in the West End at the Theatre Royal, Haymarket, under the tutelage of Sir Trevor Nunn.</span></p>
<p class="mol-para-with-font"><span>The play, and Hill with it, then toured the UK and as far afield as Canada, which also lost some 158 soldiers fighting the Taliban.</span></p>
<p class="mol-para-with-font"><span>Hill has also taken up painting. And he is rather good at it. His first attempt at interpreting his own Afghan experience on canvas was a variation of the Wiseman picture.</span></p>
<p class="mol-para-with-font"><span>Hill says: ‘The painting was taken from what I view as an iconic photo of my time in Afghanistan, showing my Company crossing the tactical line of departure before the day affected many lives. For me, the canal represents the line of crossing from friendly territory to enemy.</span></p>
<p class="mol-para-with-font"><span>‘But there are many layers to this painting and image; a departure from my military identity to my civilian one, a departure for Robbie Laws from this life to a different world; for Guy Disney, a departure of his previous physical ability; also a departure from the safety of my career to entering an enemy, new territory, thrust upon me by the shrapnel entering my brain. </span></p>
<p class="mol-para-with-font"><span>'I placed the birds on the skyline to add balance to the composition, but also the symbolism of it; birds have been interpreted as harbingers of doom. </span></p>
<p class="mol-para-with-font"><span>'The soldiers are the focal point and I have intentionally diminished the clarity of them and made them more ethereal to suggest a physical departure.’</span></p>
<p class="mol-para-with-font"><span>He adds: ‘I removed the vehicle in the centre of [Jamie Wiseman’s] photo as this distracted the viewer’s eye from the important aspect, the soldiers.’</span></p>
<p class="mol-para-with-font"><span>What then of the other soldiers in the Wiseman shot? CSM Paul Muckle — who has six children — continued in the Army. He was one of the most senior NCOs in the infantry, but was given a Late Entry Commission. Now he is Captain Muckle.</span></p>
<p class="mol-para-with-font"><span>Private Eaglesfield left the Army four weeks ago. He is now a builder, we are told, and has his life ahead of him. </span></p>
<p class="mol-para-with-font"><span>Jem McIlveen, who commanded Hill’s 6 Platoon, did a second tour of Afghanistan before leaving the Army in December 2013. He has recently married and works for Goldman Sachs in the City. He was at the gallery’s private viewing this week to support Stewart Hill.</span></p>
<p class="mol-para-with-font"><span>Robbie Laws will long be remembered, not least by Guy Disney, who commanded the vehicles captured in Jamie Wiseman’s picture of the canal crossing.</span></p>
<p class="mol-para-with-font"><span>Disney’s achievements have been extraordinary. In December 2013 he was part of Prince Harry’s Walking With Wounded team which reached the South Pole.</span></p>
<p class="mol-para-with-font"><span>This February he came third in the Royal Artillery Gold Cup at Sandown Park, thus becoming the first steeplechase jockey in racing history to ride with an artificial leg.</span></p>
<p class="mol-para-with-font"><span>Leading professional jump jockey Ruby Walsh spoke to Disney before the race and said he was glad to have been at the track to witness his achievement. ‘It’s amazing. It just goes to show that any human being who puts their mind to something can do it,’ Walsh said afterwards.</span></p>
<div class="mol-img-group xwArtSplitter">
<div class="mol-img">
<div class="image-wrap fff-pic">
<img id="i-a1c427f3c1707392" src="https://i.dailymail.co.uk/i/pix/2015/07/17/07/0CBB83E6000005DC-3164484-Disney_s_achievements_have_been_extraordinary_In_December_2013_h-a-9_1437114903927.jpg" height="803" width="962" alt="Disney’s achievements have been extraordinary. In December 2013 he was part of Prince Harry’s Walking With Wounded team which reached the South Pole. He is pictured above, second from the left" class="blkBorder img-share b-loaded">
<div class="overlay-icon mobile-gallery"><span> </span></div>
</div>
</div>
<p class="imageCaption">Disney’s achievements have been extraordinary. In December 2013 he was part of Prince Harry’s Walking With Wounded team which reached the South Pole. He is pictured above, second from the left</p>
</div>
<p class="mol-para-with-font"><span>‘I’d say it was a bigger mental battle than it ever was physical. I tip my hat to that.</span></p>
<p class="mol-para-with-font"><span>‘I think the guy is an inspiration.’</span></p>
<p class="mol-para-with-font"><span>Earlier this month Guy Disney travelled to Worcestershire to visit Wendy Laws, Robbie’s bereaved mother. ‘Guy, Stewart, Jem and others are in contact with me at this time of year,’ she told me.</span></p>
<p class="mol-para-with-font"><span>Robbie’s memory lives on. A recent fund-raising cycle ride by friends from Tower Bridge to Paris brought the Champs-Elysees to a halt.</span></p>
<p class="mol-para-with-font"><span>‘They don’t forget,’ said Mrs Laws. ‘But those who were there, they can’t forget.’</span></p>
<p class="mol-para-with-font"><span>They are touched that so high-profile an artist as Grayson Perry chose to honour their sacrifices.</span></p>
<p class="mol-para-with-font"><span>In his explanatory note when his piece was hung at the National Portrait Gallery, Perry wrote: ‘Stewart Hill showed me a photograph of a troop of soldiers crossing a shallow river in Afghanistan. It was the last photo taken before they were attacked and he received the head wound which was to change his life.’</span></p>
<p class="mol-para-with-font"><span>Perry said that he wanted his tapestry to suggest how Hill and the other soldiers were ‘crossing back over another battle line, on their return to the challenge of civilian life as a wounded soldier’.</span></p>
<p class="mol-para-with-font"><span>Hill’s Line Of Departure painting is being displayed at the 81st Annual Exhibition of the Armed Forces Arts Society, at the Mall Galleries close to Buckingham Palace. He has already been awarded two art prizes.</span></p>
<p class="mol-para-with-font"><span>On July 4, 2009, Jamie Wiseman took a number of other, more technically accomplished, photographs, which would later see him recognised by his peers at the British Press Awards. But nothing else he shot has had the lasting impact of that image of a British column marching to their fate.</span></p>
<p class="mol-para-with-font"><span><span class="mol-style-italic">The Annual Exhibition of the Armed Forces Arts Society is at the Mall Galleries until July 18. Entrance is free.</span></span></p>]]>
    </content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>https://stewarthill.co.uk/blogs/news/express-ill-do-all-i-can-to-help-others-prince-harry-to-join-wounded-heroes-on-1-000-mile-walk</id>
    <published>2015-03-18T09:31:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2019-02-05T09:32:18+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://stewarthill.co.uk/blogs/news/express-ill-do-all-i-can-to-help-others-prince-harry-to-join-wounded-heroes-on-1-000-mile-walk"/>
    <title>Express, &apos;&apos;I&apos;ll do all I can to help others&apos; Prince Harry to join wounded heroes on 1,000 mile walk.&apos;</title>
    <author>
      <name>Stewart Hill</name>
    </author>
    <content type="html">
      <![CDATA[<meta charset="utf-8">
<h3>PRINCE Harry is to join five wounded warriors on part of a 1,000 mile walk around Britain later this year to highlight issues facing injured military veterans.</h3>
<meta charset="utf-8">
<p><img src="https://cdn.images.express.co.uk/img/dynamic/106/590x/harry1-564781.jpg" alt="Prince Harry"></p>
<meta charset="utf-8">
<p>Harry met the team and asked several questions about their injuries and care, even apologising for bombarding them with so many questions because he's been "learning about it and how it all works". </p>
<p>The participants are Lt Col Stewart Hill, who suffered a brain injury in an explosion in Afghanistan in 2009, Major Elspeth de Montes, who suffers from Post Traumatic Stress Disorder, Rifleman Matt Fisher, who had his left leg amputated after a gun shot wound, Royal Marine Lance Corporal Alec Robotham who has multiple injuries from a suicide bomb incident, and Marine Scott Ransley who is blind in his right eye from a roadside bomb explosion. </p>
<p>Matt Fisher, 30, from Chertsey, Surrey, said: "I think Harry will bring a lot to this expedition in terms of publicity and support. </p>
<p>"He's a like-minded person who has his own experiences in the Army so you can relate to him still. </p>
<p>"He's had so much involvement with the rehabilitation process and its good to see he's on the ball with it and what's going on. </p>
<p>"I'm sure whenever he joins us on the walk there will be plenty of banter along the way." </p>
<p>Lt Col Hill said: "I have become the opposite - the antithesis - of what I was. </p>
<p>"From managing thousands of people to struggling to manage myself." </p>
<meta charset="utf-8">
<p>He is now hoping to become a professional artist and being helped by Walking With The Wounded with his training. </p>
<p> </p>]]>
    </content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>https://stewarthill.co.uk/blogs/news/western-telegraph-crymych-soldier-to-act-out-harrowing-war-experiences</id>
    <published>2014-01-30T15:46:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2019-02-04T15:47:06+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://stewarthill.co.uk/blogs/news/western-telegraph-crymych-soldier-to-act-out-harrowing-war-experiences"/>
    <title>Western Telegraph, &apos;Crymych soldier to act out harrowing war experiences.&apos;</title>
    <author>
      <name>Stewart Hill</name>
    </author>
    <content type="html">
      <![CDATA[<meta charset="utf-8">
<div class="article-hero light-background">
<div class="article-image-containter"><img src="https://www.westerntelegraph.co.uk/resources/images/2843639.jpg?display=1&amp;htype=100000&amp;type=responsive-gallery" alt="Lt Col Hill at the original performance at Theatre Royal Haymarket on January 22, 2012."></div>
<p class="hero-caption"><span>Lt Col Hill at the original performance at Theatre Royal Haymarket on January 22, 2012.</span></p>
</div>
<div class="article-body">
<div>
<div class="p402_hide">
<p class="article-first-paragraph">A RETIRED soldier from north Pembrokeshire is set to appear in a critically-acclaimed play based on a British soldier’s view of service, injury and recovery.</p>
<p>The Two Worlds of Charlie F is about to embark on a UK theatre tour after taking the West End by storm in January 2012.</p>
<p>Moving from the war in Afghanistan, through the dream world of morphine-induced hallucinations to the physio rooms of Headley Court, the play explores the consequences of injury, both physical and psychological, and its effects on others as the soldiers fight to win the new battle for survival at home.</p>
<p>Taken from the personal experience of wounded, injured and sick service personnel involved, The Two Worlds of Charlie F is a darkly comic, authentic and uplifting tale of survival performed by those who were there.</p>
<p>They include Lieutenant Colonel Stewart Hill, originally from Crymych, who suffered devastating injuries while fighting the Taliban in Afghanistan in July 2009.</p>
<p>He spent two and a half years in rehabilitation and suffered from a lack of identity, functioning skills, depression and anger. He was later discharged from the army.</p>
<p>The former Ysgol y Preseli pupil admits being part of the play has given him a second chance at life.</p>
<p>He said: “I felt a failure until I started work on this production. But within hours I was using my management skills to help the director and producer understand the military. Their encouragement was flattering and like the rest of the cast I felt that for the first time in a long time I had something creative and meaningful to offer.</p>
<p>“It allowed me to appreciate my contribution to life, something I thought I’d never do again.”</p>
<p>He added that the project is a vital addition to the rehabilitation schemes already put in place by the MoD. Lt Col Hill is now embarking on a career in public speaking, as well as planning to write a book about his experiences, having already found solace in military painting.</p>
<p>To find out more about the play visit www.charlie-f.com</p>
</div>
</div>
</div>]]>
    </content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>https://stewarthill.co.uk/blogs/news/western-telegraph-war-artist-fights-back-from-the-brink</id>
    <published>2013-08-10T00:00:00+01:00</published>
    <updated>2019-02-04T15:48:53+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://stewarthill.co.uk/blogs/news/western-telegraph-war-artist-fights-back-from-the-brink"/>
    <title>Western Telegraph, &apos;War artist fights back from the brink.&apos;</title>
    <author>
      <name>Stewart Hill</name>
    </author>
    <content type="html">
      <![CDATA[<meta charset="utf-8">
<p class="article-first-paragraph"><strong>A RETIRED soldier from Crymych is living proof that art therapy can help to rehabilitate injured veterans.</strong></p>
<p>The award-winning work of Lieutenant Colonel Stewart Hill has been displayed at the annual Armed Forces Art Society exhibition at the Mall Galleries in London.</p>
<p>Painting is a far cry from the 42-year-old’s army service days, when he was in command of B Company, 2 Mercian in Afghanistan.</p>
<p>On July 4, 2009 Lt Col Hill was leading 160 men in a close combat fight against the Taliban in some of the fiercest fighting seen by UK forces in Afghanistan.</p>
<p>They were in an area that had been swept for improvised explosive devices, but one had escaped detection and it was stood on by a Lance Corporal who was killed.</p>
<p>Lt Col Hill also suffered devastating injuries, including shrapnel on the brain.</p>
<p>He spent the next two-and-a-half years in rehabilitation and now suffers from a lack of functioning skills, which led to him being medically discharged from the army.</p>
<p>Faced with a life of anger, depression and a lack of identity, he was introduced to painting by artist David Mynett while on holiday. Prior to that he had not picked up a brush since taking O-Level art some 20 years before at Ysgol y Preseli.</p>
<p>His talent was evident from the start with one of his early works, an acrylic of C Company, The Royal Welsh taking pride of place in the Battalion’s Officers’ Mess.</p>
<p>More recent work from the dad-of-two is a portrait of his former colleague, Captain Rupert Bowers of 2nd Battalion, The Mercian Regiment who was killed in Afghanistan in March 2012.</p>
<p>Mr Hill told the Western Telegraph: “I adore painting; it is magical, therapeutic and exciting. To paint is to be alive. I become sucked into the subject and do not find the process exhausting. I am able to do this, which is the only thing I have managed to do wholeheartedly since my injury.</p>
<p>“I want to aspire to be recognised as a war artist. I have a wealth of ideas based on my experiences and wish to show this in my work. I do not want to glamorise war nor be anti war, but show the emotional impact of war on the many lives involved.”</p>
<p>Mr Hill now lives with his wife Melissa and daughters Annabel and Olivia in Nottingham.</p>]]>
    </content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>https://stewarthill.co.uk/blogs/news/daily-mail-betrayal-of-my-friend-the-hero-how-the-army-has-turned-its-back-on-the-suffering-of-one-of-its-bravest-men-after-he-was-nearly-killed-by-a-taliban-bomb</id>
    <published>2013-07-05T12:54:00+01:00</published>
    <updated>2019-02-04T15:44:56+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://stewarthill.co.uk/blogs/news/daily-mail-betrayal-of-my-friend-the-hero-how-the-army-has-turned-its-back-on-the-suffering-of-one-of-its-bravest-men-after-he-was-nearly-killed-by-a-taliban-bomb"/>
    <title>Daily Mail, &apos;Betrayal of my friend the hero: How the Army has turned its back on the suffering of one of its bravest men after he was nearly killed by a Taliban bomb.&apos;</title>
    <author>
      <name>Stewart Hill</name>
    </author>
    <content type="html">
      <![CDATA[<meta charset="utf-8">
<p><span>Lieutenant-Colonel Stewart Hill hands me the classified casualty list for the Light Dragoons Battle Group in the Babaji area of Afghanistan between 4 and 8 July 2009.<span> </span></span></p>
<p><span>The numbers are staggering for a low intensity war: 66 names, ranging from battlefield evacuations for heat exhaustion to KIA (killed in action).</span></p>
<p><span>Third on the list is Hill’s own name. Beside it is the acronym WIA (wounded in action). Then come the more doom-laden specifics: Head injury. Shrapnel on brain.</span></p>
<div class="artSplitter fff-pic">
<img src="https://i.dailymail.co.uk/i/pix/2013/07/05/article-2357147-076FBC28000005DC-193_634x913.jpg" height="913" width="634" alt="Still fighting: Stewart Hill with wife Melissa and daughter Olivia" class="blkBorder b-loaded">
<p class="imageCaption"><strong>Still fighting: Stewart Hill with wife Melissa and daughter Olivia</strong></p>
</div>
<p><span>Hill came within a millimetre or two of joining those KIAs on the bloodiest day of what remains the biggest British ground offensive of our soon-to-be-ended Afghan adventure. He led the infantry assault. I know, because I was there, covering the war for the Mail — only a field away when a soldier next to Hill stepped on a huge IED (improvised explosive device) and, by so doing, effectively wiped out the HQ of the British spearhead.<span> </span></span></p>
<p><span>Hill, the leader of his supporting armoured unit, his Company sergeant major, the SAS forward air controller and several other soldiers were either killed or incapacitated in the incident. The military censor didn’t allow me to report that at the time. Operationally ‘too damaging’, I was told.<span> </span></span></p>
<p><span>Hill is the most senior Afghan war neurological casualty to have been treated at the renowned Defence Medical Rehabilitation Centre at Headley Court in Surrey.</span></p>
<div data-preferred-shared-network-enabled="" class="related-carousel with-fb-or-tw news half" id="p-20" data-dm-rotator-auto-init="" data-dm-rotator-active-class="active" data-dm-rotator-page-count="1.0" data-dm-rotator-rotate="false" data-dm-rotator-page-size="1" data-dm-social-article-auto-init="" data-track-module="am-related_carousel^related_carousel" data-track-selector=".rotator-panels a:not([class*=external])" data-track-pos="static">
<div class="rotator bdrcc">
<div class="rotator-title">
<h2></h2>
</div>
</div>
<div class="fb"></div>
</div>
<p><span>Most people will associate the centre with the conflict’s many amputees, rather than casualties such as Hill who, except for the spiral wire of a hearing aid in his case, look untouched by their experience.<span> </span><br></span></p>
<p><span>But with two pieces of shrapnel too close to his brain stem to remove, and myriad associated problems, he was deeply scarred.</span></p>
<div class="floatRHS fff-pic">
<img src="https://i.dailymail.co.uk/i/pix/2013/07/05/article-2357147-1AAEA36F000005DC-164_306x423.jpg" height="423" width="306" alt="Listen up: Major Stewart Hill was a hugely respected leader - so why was he forgotten about?" class="blkBorder b-loaded">
<p class="imageCaption"><strong>Listen up: Major Stewart Hill was a hugely respected leader - so why was he forgotten about?</strong></p>
</div>
<p><span>And yet, having almost lost his life leading the bloodiest advance in our bloodiest war since the Falklands; having been invited to meet Prince Charles at Sandringham; having been a star officer identified for high rank, Hill finds himself in conflict with the Army he loved and in many respects loves still. ‘I get so angry,’ he says.</span></p>
<p><span>This week sees both the anniversary of his last battle and the deadline of his right to appeal against the Ministry of Defence’s rejection of some of his formal complaints concerning his treatment following his near-fatal wound.<span> </span></span></p>
<p><span>Stewart Hill is a remarkable man. But his life has been turned upside down. When he joined the Army, he accepted the possibility of serious injury or death in the line of duty. What he did not expect, though, was what he alleges to have happened: abandonment at the time of his greatest need.<span> </span></span></p>
<p><span>The facts that are accepted by the Ministry of Defence are shaming enough. In the five-and-a-half months after he first left Headley Court, Hill did not receive a single care visit from his unit. According to regulations, they should have been fortnightly.</span></p>
<p><span>The military bureaucracy was also so poor that even though he had a serious brain injury, the records showed him to be fit and ready to deploy. The people who could have helped him didn’t know for months.</span></p>
<p><span>And so he and his family were left alone to cope.</span></p>
<p><span>Today, the father-of-two, who received a financial package for his wounds and a pension, says: ‘To attract new recruits, the Army promotes itself as an organisation that cares. There is the Military Covenant of loyalty, integrity and moral courage.</span></p>
<p><span>‘But these virtues were non-existent in my case. It didn’t mean a thing.<span> </span></span></p>
<p><span>‘My wife, Melissa, and I felt that we were forgotten. I was badly wounded and so I simply didn’t matter any more.’ And in that respect, he says, he is far from being alone.<span> </span></span></p>
<p><span>I first met the then Major Hill in June 2009 at Forward Operating Base Price, a heat-scoured frontline camp in the Taliban heartland of Helmand Province.</span></p>
<p><span>Hill’s parent regiment was The Royal Welsh — his family farms in West Wales. But, in 2007, he had been seconded to the 2nd battalion of the newly formed Mercian Regiment. He was put in command of B Company. During the Afghan summer tour of 2009, 2nd Mercian was attached to the Light Dragoons Battle Group.</span></p>
<p><span>These were critical times for the British military effort in Helmand. Operation Panther’s Claw, the biggest UK ground offensive of the war, was about to enter its climactic stage.</span></p>
<div class="clear"></div>
<div class="artSplitter fff-pic">
<img src="https://i.dailymail.co.uk/i/pix/2013/07/05/article-2357147-076FC564000005DC-917_634x426.jpg" height="426" width="634" alt="High regard: Hill was esteemed enough to meet Prince Charles at Sandringham" class="blkBorder b-loaded">
<p class="imageCaption"><strong>High regard: Hill was esteemed enough to meet Prince Charles at Sandringham</strong></p>
</div>
<p><span>The Mercians and the armour of the Light Dragoons were to move across the Nahr-e-Bagra canal and fight on towards positions seized by the Scots and Welsh Guards. It would not be easy. The Taliban had held the ground for two years.</span></p>
<p><span>The Welsh Guards’ own CO, Lt-Col Rupert Thorneloe (a friend of Prince Charles) had been killed by an IED only a few days before — the most senior British fatality of the war. His death cast a pall over the whole operation.</span></p>
<p><span>Hill, then 38, conducted last briefings before zero hour.</span></p>
<p><span>In an inspirational speech, he said to the junior ranks: ‘Is it to be the insurgents’ summer or will it belong to us? Of course, it’s going to be ours.’<span> </span></span></p>
<p><span>On that night, Stewart Hill and B Company slept amid hens and goats in a farmyard compound.<span> </span><br></span></p>
<p><span>Above them was an astonishing sky, filled with stars and arcing red tracer as a Danish army picket fought off a Taliban attack further along the canal.<span> </span></span></p>
<p><span>By 9.15am on July 4, the battle group had moved out and, within the hour, it was engaged by the first of a series of sharp ambushes in a hot, claustrophobic countryside of tree-lined fields and drainage channels.</span></p>
<p><span>At times the fighting was both close and intense. I recall in one crisis being offered a pistol by a sergeant major who declared: ‘We are in the ****ing s*** here.’ Then he settled the matter with the old-fashioned expedient of a hand grenade thrown over a wall.<span> </span></span></p>
<div class="clear">
<span>When he finally awoke, four medical staff had to hold him down as he tried to escape the ward. In his confusion, Hill believed he had been captured by the Taliban</span>  <span>But as the light faded, fortune frowned on Hill’s command. The lead armoured vehicle accompanying his HQ group was hit by a rocket propelled grenade. Eighteen-year-old Private Robbie Laws was killed and several others wounded. A helicopter evacuated the casualties.<span> </span></span>
</div>
<div class="clear"><span><span></span></span></div>
<p><span>As Hill and his HQ moved away from the landing ground, Lance Corporal David Dennis stepped on the devastating IED. Of those who had started out that morning, three were now dead and many more wounded.<span> </span></span></p>
<p><span>That night, I was told that Hill would also die. He survived. But his world had changed for ever.</span><br><span>Hill was flown from Afghanistan to the Queen Elizabeth Hospital in Birmingham where he underwent life-saving brain surgery.</span></p>
<p><span>When he finally awoke, four medical staff had to hold him down as he tried to escape the ward. In his confusion, Hill believed he had been captured by the Taliban. Five weeks later he was transferred to Headley Court.<span> </span></span></p>
<p><span>It seems extraordinary now, considering what had happened, but Hill remained there for less than a month before being discharged and put on ‘home sick leave’.<span> </span></span></p>
<div class="clear"></div>
<div class="artSplitter fff-pic">
<img src="https://i.dailymail.co.uk/i/pix/2013/07/05/article-2357147-1AAEA367000005DC-129_634x401.jpg" height="401" width="634" alt="Inspirational: Major Stewart Hill, O.C of B Company, The Mercians, gives a pep talk to his soldiers before leading them into battle for Operation Panther Claw, in Helmand, Afghanistan" class="blkBorder b-loaded">
<p class="imageCaption"><strong>Inspirational: Major Stewart Hill, O.C of B Company, The Mercians, gives a pep talk to his soldiers before leading them into battle for Operation Panther Claw, in Helmand, Afghanistan</strong></p>
</div>
<p><span>He admits that this was partly due to his own ‘disorientation’ and his insistence that he was on the road to full recovery.<span> </span></span></p>
<p><span>‘It was far too early,’ he says. ‘I had totally unrealistic expectations of my immediate future. I thought I was fine, but I wasn’t. Yet I was discharged and put on a ‘Gradual Return To Work programme’.</span></p>
<p><span>This is when the serious ‘mismanagement’ of his case began, says Hill.<span> </span></span></p>
<p><span>‘I had a major brain injury, but no individual or organisation took responsibility for me.’</span></p>
<div class="clear">Although a Royal Welsh, because he had been wounded while serving with 2 Mercian, the latter was responsible for his care and rehab. Their depot was a barracks in Belfast, which was inconvenient for his family who were based in the English Midlands.</div>
<p><span>In his confused state, Hill thought he could now make the first steps towards a return to duty. He asked if he could have a desk at a barracks in Nottinghamshire where his wife worked as a civil servant.<span> </span></span></p>
<p><span>The Mercians agreed. And so Hill spent weeks there, playing solitaire on a computer and following B Company’s progress on the internet.<span> </span></span></p>
<p><span>‘I was hiding in a corner and everyone seemed happy with that,’ he says.<span> </span></span></p>
<p><span>But it seems that no one in authority really understood — or cared — how badly injured he was.</span><br><span>A civilian GP at the barracks gave him a ‘28-day light duties’ chit. It was as if he’d merely sprained an ankle.<span> </span></span></p>
<div class="moduleHalf">
<span>Outwardly, he did. But this superficial appearance hid a catalogue of problems</span><span> </span>
</div>
<p><span>Later, 2 Mercian could not provide any welfare or unit health board records.<span> </span></span></p>
<p><span>They had been ‘lost’ and suggested clearly that insufficient care was being taken of his recovery.<span> </span></span><br><span>Gradually, he began to feel ‘as if something was wrong’ with both himself and his treatment.</span></p>
<p><span>‘Melissa would ask me to go shopping. But by the time I had got to the shop, I had forgotten why I was there. Or, if she asked me to get a particular brand, I would get frightened and confused if I couldn’t find it.<span> </span></span></p>
<p><span>‘I was the antithesis of the Army leader I had been.’</span></p>
<p><span>If only he had lost a limb, it would be obvious that something was wrong, he sometimes felt.</span></p>
<p><span>One weekday evening, at Waterloo station, I met Hill unofficially for the first time since our tour together. We were to have dinner.<span> </span></span></p>
<p><span>‘Stewart, you look great,’ I began, meaning it.</span></p>
<p><span>The reaction was startling. ‘No!’ he said firmly. ‘Stop right there!’<span> </span></span></p>
<p><span>And from his pocket he produced a piece of A4 paper on which was printed a description of his true condition. Embarrassingly for me, it began with the words: ‘Most people who meet me now say: “Stewart, you look great”.’</span></p>
<div class="clear"></div>
<div class="artSplitter fff-pic">
<img src="https://i.dailymail.co.uk/i/pix/2013/07/05/article-2357147-1AAEA363000005DC-418_634x473.jpg" height="473" width="634" alt="In the line of fire: Hill came close to losing his life for the Army - yet he has been let down in the aftermath" class="blkBorder b-loaded">
<p class="imageCaption"><strong>In the line of fire: Hill came close to losing his life for the Army - yet he has been let down in the aftermath</strong></p>
</div>
<p><span>Outwardly, he did. But this superficial appearance hid a catalogue of problems: memory loss, short attention span, lack of concentration, poor balance and gait, exhaustion, headaches, bursts of irrational temper, lack of insight or empathy, hearing loss and ‘severe and persistent tinnitus’. He also suffered depression.</span></p>
<p><span>But where was the support from 2 Mercian who, he says, he had ‘almost given my life for’?</span></p>
<p><span>An officer of equal or senior rank was supposed to visit him every two weeks. Each month, there should have been a case review. But nothing happened.</span></p>
<p><span>In October 2009, Hill travelled to Belfast for B Company’s homecoming from Afghanistan. He also attended the annual regimental dinner shortly afterwards and was at a medal ceremony at Sandringham that November.</span></p>
<p><span>Cynically, his battalion would cite their contact at these events as evidence of the active execution of their duty of care. Hill denies this and says his attendance was instigated by himself.</span></p>
<p><span>Later, the Mercians would admit that contact was ‘perhaps not all it should have been’.</span></p>
<p><span>This was blamed on the CO being in Afghanistan and the lack of a permanent leader of the battalion’s UK-based rear HQ. By the time the CO returned, ‘he inherited a situation which had already gone wrong’, the battalion argued. But then still nothing happened.</span></p>
<div class="moduleHalf">
<span>He met other injured soldiers who claimed to  have been similarly neglected by their units</span> </div>
<p><span>Hill asked to be transferred to another unit that would care for him properly. But again he says that neither 2 Mercian nor the Royal Welsh had shown interest.</span></p>
<p><span>Friends told him to make an official complaint. But he remained loyal to the organisation and held back, choosing, instead, in February 2010, to write to the Adjutant General of the British Army, setting out what had happened.</span></p>
<p><span>I have seen the letter he received in reply from the officer, Lt-General Mark Mans.</span><br><span>‘Dear Stewart,’ it began. ‘It is clear from what you have written that the boundaries of who was responsible for you became blurred. As a consequence, you did not receive the level of attention you needed and that more of an effort could have been made to maintain contact and provide the necessary support.<span> </span></span></p>
<p><span>‘It is experiences like yours that allow me to improve continually the system and I will ensure that we learn from what has happened to you.’ Yet, as far as his case was concerned, still nothing happened.<span> </span></span><br><span>(General Mans has since left the Army and is now working in the private sector for Capita.)</span></p>
<p><span>By then, Hill had been transferred out of the ‘care’ of the Mercians and into the Army’s 5th Division. An outpatient review led him to be re-admitted to Headley Court where he stayed until the summer of 2010.<span> </span></span></p>
<p><span>There, he says, he met other injured soldiers who claimed to  have been similarly neglected by their units. The Army simply could not cope with fighting a war and looking after its many wounded.<span> </span></span><br><span>It was only after being treated at a civilian neurological centre in Leeds that his brain impairment was recognised.</span></p>
<div class="clear"></div>
<div class="artSplitter fff-pic">
<img src="https://i.dailymail.co.uk/i/pix/2013/07/05/article-2357147-1AAEA36B000005DC-973_634x431.jpg" height="431" width="634" alt="One of the best: Hill gives a pep talk to his soldiers before leading them into battle" class="blkBorder b-loaded">
<p class="imageCaption"><strong>One of the best: Hill gives a pep talk to his soldiers before leading them into battle</strong></p>
</div>
<p><span>By August 2010, Hill had become so angry about his experience and the Mercians’ excuses that he submitted a 15-point official complaint. However, this was rejected by the MoD for being ‘out of time’. Hill won an overruling, though, after pointing out that recovery from his brain wound had been his immediate priority.</span></p>
<p><span>When, just after his wounding, Hill was still considered to be the Army’s top candidate for promotion to Lt-Colonel, Major General Tim Radford, then commander of British troops in Afghanistan, wrote of him: ‘Major Hill has commanded B Company 2 Mercian brilliantly … in some of the fiercest fighting seen by UK forces in Afghanistan. He was superb: incisive, instinctive, confident and brave. Prior to [that]… he was urbane and utterly charming.<span> </span></span></p>
<p><span>‘Major Hill has been one of my rising stars. He is an officer of intellect and confidence who is widely respected by his men.’</span></p>
<p><span>Considering this encomium, it is hard to believe how he was subsequently treated. Indeed, others outside the Army have better recognised his talents.<span> </span></span></p>
<p><span>Two of his poems have been published in an anthology, and he has appeared for one night on the West End stage in a Trevor  Nunn-directed play about the Afghan War.</span></p>
<p><span>Grayson Perry, the cross-dressing, Turner Prize-winning artist, has also chosen Hill as one of only three among thousands of the Afghan wounded to immortalise in paint.<span> </span></span></p>
<p><span>Hill’s own paintings, too, are startlingly good. And this is what the future probably holds for him. His portrait of a fellow Mercian officer, killed last year, has just won the Army’s Templar Award for art.</span><br><span>Meanwhile, the MoD, which is still using pictures of Hill to promote ‘leadership’, is fighting off his Service Complaint.</span></p>
<p><span>Of his 15 specific complaints, six were recently upheld, but the majority dismissed. He can appeal. Hill simply wants the MoD to admit that it was wrong. The Army’s top brass, though, are loath to do so.<span> </span></span></p>
<p><span>I have seen a letter written in 2010 which showed that they were already concerned that Hill might go public about his situation. The 5th Division commander, Major General Martin Rutledge, wrote: ‘Stewart … talked about discussing his treatment with the Press … While Stewart’s case does not sit on a high profile or ministerial desk, it clearly has the potential to do so.’ Maybe it will now.</span><br><span>Stewart Hill realised a long time ago that he could no longer be a senior soldier. His final medical board was in November 2011. He was formally discharged last year, but allowed to use the rank of Lt-Colonel.<span> </span></span></p>
<p><span>On Thursday, he travelled to Worcestershire to visit the grave of Private Robbie Laws.</span></p>
<p><span>Unlike some of his superiors, at least Lt-Col Stewart Hill (retired) remains loyal to the men who served under him.</span></p>]]>
    </content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>https://stewarthill.co.uk/blogs/news/the-daily-telegraph-the-hurt-of-the-hidden-wound</id>
    <published>2012-12-16T15:32:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2019-02-04T15:34:45+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://stewarthill.co.uk/blogs/news/the-daily-telegraph-the-hurt-of-the-hidden-wound"/>
    <title>The Daily Telegraph, &apos;The hurt of the hidden wound.&apos;</title>
    <author>
      <name>Stewart Hill</name>
    </author>
    <content type="html">
      <![CDATA[<meta charset="utf-8">
<div class="storyHead">
<h1 itemprop="headline name">The hurt of the hidden wound</h1>
<h2 itemprop="alternativeHeadline description">Stewart Hill suffered a devastating brain injury in an IED blast in Afghanistan. Then he became involved with the On Course Foundation</h2>
<div class="artIntro">
<div id="storyEmbSlide">
<div class="slideshow ssIntro">
<div class="nextPrevLayer">
<div class="ssImg">
<img src="https://secure.i.telegraph.co.uk/multimedia/archive/02429/stewart-hill_2429482b.jpg" width="620" height="388" alt="'Many positives’: Stewart Hill with his wife Melissa and daughter Annabel at their home near Nottingham" itemprop="image">
<div class="artImageExtras">
<div class="ingCaptionCredit">
<span class="caption">'Many positives’: Stewart Hill with his wife Melissa and daughter Annabel at their home near Nottingham</span> </div>
<div class="ingCaptionCredit"></div>
<div class="ingCaptionCredit">By Bryony Gordon </div>
</div>
</div>
</div>
</div>
</div>
</div>
</div>
<div class="oneHalf gutter">
<div class="story">
<div class="cl"></div>
<div class="byline">
<div class="cl"></div>
</div>
<div id="mainBodyArea" itemprop="articleBody">
<div class="firstPar">
<p>It was July 4, 2009 when Lieutenant Colonel Stewart Hill had his independence taken away from him. But he doesn’t remember much of what happened on that hot, dusty Saturday, and has no recollection at all of the moment the lights went out on his former life for ever.</p>
</div>
<div class="secondPar">
<p>His last memory was of a Chinook helicopter rising from a ploughed Afghan field. It carried the lifeless body of 18-year-old Private Robert Laws and other injured men of the Light Dragoons and 2 Mercian, victims of an attack with rocket-propelled grenades by the Taliban. After that, the gaps have to be filled in by others.</p>
</div>
<div class="thirdPar">
<p>Although Hill was in an area that had been swept with metal detectors for improvised explosive devices (IEDs), one had escaped detection. After the helicopter had taken off, Lance Corporal David Dennis stepped on an IED and was killed. Hill, who was in command of 160 men, was blown into a hedge by the explosion. As he says now, these things happen – they are simply the cold and cruel reality of war. He was found curled up in the foetal position, his radio antenna embedded in his skull.</p>
</div>
<div class="fourthPar">
<p>He also had shrapnel lodged in his cerebellum (part of the brain at the back of the skull) and had badly bruised the frontal lobe of his brain. On the flight back to the UK, the plane had to land twice for fear that the medical team was losing him, but he made it back alive to the Queen Elizabeth hospital in Birmingham.</p>
</div>
<div class="fifthPar">
<p>Today, there is little to show that he was blown up by an IED. He lost none of his limbs and suffered no disfigurement. The only physical signs that something might be wrong are the hearing aids fitted to both ears – his eardrums were perforated in the blast.</p>
</div>
<div class="body">
<p>The casual observer would probably not notice that when 41-year-old Hill goes to make a coffee, he forgets to put a cup in the machine. You might attribute the fact that he frequently rubs his temple to tiredness. He is tired. Sometimes, he needs 14 hours’ sleep a night, and even then he wakes up exhausted, unable to function properly because he has what is known as a traumatic brain injury (TBI) – his so-called “executive functioning” damaged, and with it his ability to concentrate or pay attention or to process information. His sense of taste and smell barely exist.</p>
<p>When he talks about himself, he refers to his “old” and his “new” brain. With the new brain has come a personality change that makes him barely recognisable from the tough-talking Army man of the past. “I went from commanding 160 men to struggling to command myself,” he states simply.</p>
<p>But he is, as he says now, “in a fairly easy position. I have post-traumatic amnesia, which means I don’t remember anything from half an hour before the accident to about three weeks after it – the worst three weeks of my life, essentially.”</p>
<p>His wife does, however. Melissa, 40, has a clear memory of everything, from the moment she received a knock on the door “at about 10 to one in the morning on the Sunday”, through to today, as we sit among the Christmas decorations in their family home just outside Nottingham. Their two-year-old daughter Annabel drives a toy car through the kitchen; their 12-year-old Olivia is at school.</p>
<p>“It can be quite difficult living with a toddler, an adolescent and a man with a brain injury,” is Melissa’s wry response when asked how she finds things.</p>
<p>The men from the Ministry of Defence told Melissa that her husband – they have been together since she was 19 – had a serious head wound and was unlikely to survive. The next evening she was told that they were considering bringing Stewart back to the UK, assessing whether or not he would survive the flight. “The hardest thing was Olivia. I had nothing to say to her because I didn’t know how badly injured he was. She was only nine.</p>
<p>“When I eventually told her, I said that I had some bad news. She said 'Has Nanna’s dog died?’ and I said no, the dog was fine. And then she said 'Is it Daddy?’ and she just screamed. It was awful.”</p>
<p>When Melissa first saw her husband in hospital, “he looked oddly fit. He had a tan from being out in the sun and was all pumped up from the work. There was just a bandage around his head. It wasn’t what you expected to see from a man who had just been seriously injured in Afghanistan.”</p>
<p>But she was about to learn that even though his body was fully intact, his mind was not. Despite an operation to remove the shrapnel from his cerebellum, two pieces had to be left in. “They were 2mm from the spinal cord and could have paralysed him,” she says.</p>
<p>After the operation, he was put into a coma. When he woke for the first time, a week after he had been admitted to hospital, he thought it was 2002. He did not recognise his brother. Several times, he had to be told that men had died during the operation that had injured him, and each time he would cry.</p>
<p>He didn’t believe anything was wrong with him – “I told Melissa that I was like Jack Nicholson in One Flew Over the Cuckoo’s Nest, and that it was all a conspiracy” – and he became paranoid that people were trying to get him, that planes would fall out of the sky and kill everyone around him.</p>
<p>“I had woken up with a different husband,” says Melissa. “He hadn’t lost a limb, but sometimes I wondered if maybe it would have been easier if he had. At least he would still be the same person he was before he went to Afghanistan.”</p>
<p>As well as having a serious brain injury, Hill was deeply depressed, and depression was something he had previously seen as a sign of weakness. He just wanted to get back to Afghanistan, to start fighting again. “I missed the leading,” he says, starkly. “I missed commanding my men.”</p>
<p>He was desperate to leave hospital. He spent five weeks in the Queen Elizabeth, then a further four at the Defence Medical Rehabilitation Centre at Headley Court, in Surrey. But after six months at home, pretending everything was OK, he accepted that things most definitely weren’t and returned to Headley Court for more help. It was there that he discovered that playing golf could be an important part of his rehabilitation.</p>
<p>“It quietened my mind, and more importantly, it got me outside,” he says.</p>
<p>It was through this introduction to the game that he became involved with the On Course Foundation, a charity dedicated to training injured Servicemen in a sport that they can play competitively and enjoy, that will assist their physical and mental recovery, and that can lead to a new career.</p>
<p>Without On Course, he isn’t sure how he would have muddled through. “It enabled me to be with like-minded people, to stay in with the military way of doing things – it is hard, when the Services are your life, to suddenly have all that taken away from you.”</p>
<p>In March of this year, he was discharged from the Army. He has put in a service complaint against the Ministry of Defence, because he feels that the care he received after the injury simply wasn’t good enough. “That makes me cross, more so than the injury,” says Melissa. “He got most of his rehabilitation from places like On Course.”</p>
<p>Today he is the charity’s employment officer, working three days a week to help find jobs for other injured Servicemen. “It has been a huge boost to his confidence and his self-esteem,” says Melissa. “Because all of that goes when you experience what Stewart has.”</p>
<p>And the injury has brought unexpected changes to the Hill household. “Having a new husband is not necessarily a bad thing. Before, his work came first and we came second. Olivia barely knew her father while she was growing up. He was the kind of man who volunteered for tours of Afghanistan without telling me.</p>
<p>“But what has changed is that he has learnt the value of family. Annabel spends all her time with him, and Olivia has her daddy back. So there are positives. There are many positives.”</p>
</div>
</div>
</div>
</div>]]>
    </content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>https://stewarthill.co.uk/blogs/news/daily-mail-a-hero-led-hours-inspiring-troops-major-hill-lies-wounded-comrades-dead</id>
    <published>2009-07-07T12:42:00+01:00</published>
    <updated>2019-02-04T12:48:52+00:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://stewarthill.co.uk/blogs/news/daily-mail-a-hero-led-hours-inspiring-troops-major-hill-lies-wounded-comrades-dead"/>
    <title>Daily Mail, &apos;A hero led Hours inspiring troops Major Hill lies wounded comrades dead.&apos;</title>
    <author>
      <name>Stewart Hill</name>
    </author>
    <content type="html">
      <![CDATA[<meta charset="utf-8">
<h2>Three dead and inspiring commander seriously wounded: A terrifyingly graphic despatch from the Afghan frontline.</h2>
<meta charset="utf-8">
<p><em>By Richard Pendlebury and Jamie Wiseman</em></p>
<p><span>They caught us out in the open, some way from cover and at almost point-blank range. But for their poor marksmanship, that would have been that.<span> </span><br></span></p>
<p><span>We were in the front section of six men, half-way across a ploughed field, when automatic fire from at least two Taliban fighters about 80 yards to our front right came crackling past us.<span> </span><br></span></p>
<p>'Go firm!' someone shouted, meaning that we should get down immediately. Then, a heartbeat later, with our noses in the dust and the crackle intensifying: 'We can't stay here. Get to cover, move, move, move!'</p>
<meta charset="utf-8">
<p><img src="https://i.dailymail.co.uk/i/pix/2009/07/07/article-1197946-059A2E40000005DC-43_634x423.jpg" alt="Troops"><strong>Troops blast their way through compounds in the Green Zone</strong></p>
<p><span>So we staggered up under the weight of our packs and ran. Our luck held, we made the treeline ahead of us, plunged through a screen of bamboo and slid waist-deep into a filthy irrigation canal.</span></p>
<p><span>A few feet away on the far bank, the mud walls of a compound loomed. On the other side of the wall, the Taliban were exchanging fire with the rest of 6 Platoon, B Company 2nd Mercian Regiment, who were pinned down out in the field.</span></p>
<p><span>As we hauled ourselves onto the far bank of the waterway, our own situation clarified.</span></p>
<p><span>It was not a good position to be in. We had no idea how many of the enemy were a wall's width away. With a civilian Afghan interpreter in tow, alongside photographer Jamie Wiseman and myself, three of our party of six were unarmed.</span></p>
<p><span>Platoon leader Lieutenant Jem McIlveen turned and put his fingers to his lips to signal silence. The Taliban were that close. 'Do you want a gun?' hissed the sergeant major, who had a pistol as well as his rifle. 'I'm serious - do you want a gun?'</span></p>
<p>'No, I don't think so, thank you.' 'Well, if you change your mind, just ask. We are in the ****ing s**t here.'</p>
<meta charset="utf-8">
<p><img src="https://i.dailymail.co.uk/i/pix/2009/07/07/article-1197946-059A274D000005DC-893_634x392.jpg"><strong>Men from 6 Platoon, B company, 2 Mercians, scramble for cover in the first contact with Taliban fighters</strong></p>
<meta charset="utf-8">
<p><strong><img src="https://i.dailymail.co.uk/i/pix/2009/07/07/article-1197946-059A2D8E000005DC-455_634x425.jpg"></strong></p>
<meta charset="utf-8">
<p><strong><span>Troops blast their way through compounds during Green Zone battles as part of Operation Panther's Claw</span></strong></p>
<meta charset="utf-8">
<p><span>As we pressed our backs to the wall, the firefight a few metres from us intensified.<span> </span><br></span></p>
<p><span>Out in the field, the platoon had brought to bear at least one belt-fed general-purpose machine gun - known to the soldiers as the 'jimpy' - and were hammering away at targets to our immediate left.</span></p>
<p><span>It was then that the sergeant major, a grizzled 49-year-old sniper specialist, made his move. As I watched him, he took a hand grenade from a pouch, stepped forward to where the wall of the compound turned a corner and lobbed it over the parapet.</span></p>
<p><span>There was tremendous bang, a swirl of dust and the firing from inside the compound ceased.</span></p>
<p><span>'Wahoo! Go get 'em, Diamonds!' a Mercian yelled from the field, referring to the regiment's diamond shoulder flash. The tide had turned.</span></p>
<p><span>Moments later, an Apache attack helicopter swooped in to strafe a compound nearby, where three Taliban with rocket-propelled grenades (RPGs) had been spotted. Swinging round, the Apache then launched a Hellfire missile.<span> </span><br></span></p>
<p><span>With an incoming banshee shriek followed by a tooth-rattling boom, the Hellfire hit its target. The battle, so suddenly joined, was over. For the moment.</span></p>
<meta charset="utf-8">
<p><span><img src="https://i.dailymail.co.uk/i/pix/2009/07/07/article-1197946-059A2EF0000005DC-890_306x465.jpg" alt="Major Stewart Hill"><img src="https://i.dailymail.co.uk/i/pix/2009/07/07/article-1197946-059A259B000005DC-435_306x465.jpg"></span></p>
<meta charset="utf-8">
<p><strong>Major Stewart Hill, OC of B Company, addresses his men before leading them into battle. Right, an unnamed British soldier watches a helicopter carrying casualties fly off</strong></p>
<meta charset="utf-8">
<p><strong><img src="https://i.dailymail.co.uk/i/pix/2009/07/07/article-1197946-059A30FA000005DC-925_634x422.jpg" alt="Trench warfare"></strong></p>
<meta charset="utf-8"><meta charset="utf-8">
<p><strong>Trench warfare: Troops arrange defensive positions after being pinned down by the Taliban</strong></p>
<meta charset="utf-8">
<p><span>his was just one incident of many in the first day of combat for 6 Platoon.</span></p>
<p><span>They were the spearhead infantry unit in the main thrust of Operation Panther's Claw, the biggest British ground offensive against the Taliban.<span> </span><br></span></p>
<p><span>The troops are operating in the Malgir and Babaji areas, south west of Gereshk, which have been controlled by the Taliban for almost two years.</span></p>
<p><span>Mail photographer Jamie and I were embedded with the platoon, as they experienced firefight after firefight, pressing on aggressively through a number of ambushes, in countryside infested with Improvised Explosive Devices (IEDs) - the lethal homemade bombs that have claimed so many British lives.<span> </span><br></span></p>
<div class="clear"></div>
<p><span>The first hours had gone well. But as daylight faded, B Company began to take casualties.</span></p>
<p><span>By nightfall three men were dead: one Mercian, one Light Dragoon, and an attached Afghan soldier. At least eight others were listed as wounded or suffering from heat exhaustion, several of them in a serious condition.</span></p>
<p><span>This is the story of that first day of combat, from the perspective of a British frontline infantry platoon.</span></p>
<p><span>Chickens, sheep and goats picked their way among 6 Platoon as they slept in a farmyard on the eve of battle.<span> </span></span></p>
<meta charset="utf-8">
<p><span><span><img src="https://i.dailymail.co.uk/i/pix/2009/07/07/article-1197946-059A2D00000005DC-384_634x530.jpg"></span></span></p>
<meta charset="utf-8">
<p><strong>Soldiers take shelter in a garden after extracting themselves from a prolonged firefight with the Taliban</strong></p>
<meta charset="utf-8">
<p><strong><img src="https://i.dailymail.co.uk/i/pix/2009/07/07/article-1197946-059A1C7D000005DC-259_634x469.jpg"></strong></p>
<meta charset="utf-8">
<p><strong><span>Battle weary: Soldiers rest up in a field at the end of another long day</span></strong></p>
<meta charset="utf-8">
<p><span>'Stand to' (the order get ready for action) took place at first light, around 4.15am. We moved across their start line - a causeway over the Nahr-e-Bagra canal - five hours later.</span></p>
<p><span>Swallows darted overhead as the soldiers pushed into the 'green zone' of agricultural land beyond.</span></p>
<p><span>This was dangerous terrain for footslogging. The IED threat was very high and increasingly sophisticated.<span> </span><br></span></p>
<p><span>Only last week one of these bombs claimed the life of Lieutenant-Colonel Rupert Thorneloe, the highest-ranking British officer to die in combat since the Falklands War back in 1982.</span></p>
<p><span>And so, our platoon was led at all times by soldiers using mine detectors. 'The bravest of the brave,' as Lt McIlveen called them.</span></p>
<p><span>The platoon leader, aged 26 and from Oxfordshire, had reminded his men to be 'very aggressive' in this perfect ambush country of small fields, treelines, water courses and farm compounds.<span> </span><br></span></p>
<div class="clear">'If we get contacted (fired upon) I want you to lay down as much firepower as you can. They're going to be the ones who have to keep their heads down, not us.'</div>
<div class="clear"></div>
<div class="clear">
<meta charset="utf-8">
<img src="https://i.dailymail.co.uk/i/pix/2009/07/07/article-1197946-059A1D2B000005DC-998_634x296.jpg">
</div>
<div class="clear">
<meta charset="utf-8">
<strong>Hundreds of B company troops are pictured as they advance into the battle ground on the second day of the advance into the Green Zone</strong>
</div>
<div class="clear"><strong></strong></div>
<div class="clear">
<meta charset="utf-8">
<p><span>We did not have long to wait. A little after 10.30am the platoon was crossing an irrigation channel, lined with trees, when bursts of accurate AK-47 fire began to crack past us.</span></p>
<p><span>The most exposed soldier, Lance Corporal Gaz James, launched himself neck-deep into the water as his colleagues went to ground along the bank and began to seek the shooters.</span></p>
<p><span>One of the jimpy machine guns opened up, deafeningly, next to me, at a compound 500 metres across a field. Then the rest of the platoon began to blaze away, calling out sightings and warnings.</span></p>
<p><span>'Two possible firing points.'<span> </span><br></span></p>
<p><span>'Look to that pile of corn. Two knuckles right.'</span></p>
<p><span>'Fire from the right!' 'Everyone OK that side?'<span> </span><br></span></p>
<p><span>Then came a 'whoosh' and a Taliban Rocket Propelled Grenade (RPG) streaked across the field in our direction, but passed some way over our heads.<span> </span><br></span></p>
<p><span>'Who fired that, Stevie Wonder?' joked one of the men, referring to the blind soul singer. Silence fell. A large white butterfly fluttered right across the muzzles of the British guns.</span></p>
<p><span>The forward part of the platoon, who had crossed the channel, pushed through tree cover to try to flank the enemy.<span> </span><br></span></p>
<p>There was some discussion about the Taliban fighters already fired upon. The platoon sniper thought he had 'dropped one'. Another soldier also claimed a possible kill.</p>
<meta charset="utf-8">
<p><img src="https://i.dailymail.co.uk/i/pix/2009/07/07/article-1197946-059A2B3A000005DC-181_634x404.jpg"></p>
<meta charset="utf-8">
<p><strong>Under fire: Mail writer Richard Pendlebury scrambles for cover</strong></p>
<meta charset="utf-8">
<p><strong><img src="https://i.dailymail.co.uk/i/pix/2009/07/07/article-1197946-0599A786000005DC-611_634x422.jpg"></strong></p>
<meta charset="utf-8">
<p><strong><span>Two Scimitar Armoured Recconnaisance Vehicles and a Spartan Tank (centre) pictured on the second day of the advance into the Green Zone</span></strong></p>
<meta charset="utf-8">
<p><span>But the respite was brief. An interpreter who had a radio to monitor Taliban communications reported that they were about to attack again. The platoon finished crossing the canal and moved on.</span></p>
<p><span>We'd travelled just a few hundred yards when a fusillade of small arms fire broke out on our left flank. 'Contact from front. One single firer,' came the message down the line. Our sniper moved up the column and someone remarked: 'He's about to give the Taliban the good news.'</span></p>
<p><span>Hot work: already more than 40c with 'dust devil' whirlwinds dancing across the parched, claustrophobic landscape. The platoon, each carrying at least 55kg on their backs, as well as their weapons, pressed on.<span> </span><br></span></p>
<p><span>More Taliban radio chatter, deciphered by our interpreter. They would attack 'in ten minutes'. An NCO's reply was typically pugnacious: 'What, are they having a f***ing teabreak? Bring it on!'</span></p>
<p><span>They tried to. At 12.28pm there was another burst of inaccurate fire. But half an hour later came the ambush in which six of us were cut off and the firefight, which, as I described earlier, ended with the British grenade and Hellfire missile.<span> </span><br></span></p>
<div class="clear">After it was over, the sergeant major called for 'dry fags'. Alas, I cannot name him because 'my missus thinks I am safe in an office in Camp Bastion [the British HQ in Helmand]'.</div>
<div class="clear"></div>
<div class="clear">
<meta charset="utf-8">
<img src="https://i.dailymail.co.uk/i/pix/2009/07/07/article-1197946-0594B494000005DC-905_634x391.jpg">
</div>
<div class="clear">
<meta charset="utf-8">
<strong>Pictured in the background are Danish Armoured vehicles who provided initial support</strong>
</div>
<div class="clear"><strong></strong></div>
<div class="clear">
<meta charset="utf-8">
<p><span>'Good work, boys,' said Lt McIlveen. I noticed that on the back of his rucksack he had sewn the motto: 'Stand Firm. Strike Hard.'</span></p>
<p><span>An hour later the platoon was still lying in the shade along the irrigation channel. Taliban radio suggested their fighters were trying to surround us. 'Charming,' drawled one soldier.</span></p>
<p><span>As the tension grew, a man in traditional white 'dish dash' robe was seen moving along the opposite treeline. 'Shall I drop him?' asked the sniper.</span></p>
<p><span>The lieutenant and his NCOs studied the figure through telescopic sights: 'No, he's an old man. A stubborn old man who won't leave the battlefield.'</span></p>
<p><span>With reports coming in that the insurgents were 'ready to attack' us, the lieutenant decided we had to change our position. Immediately.</span></p>
<p><span>To avoid being channelled into another likely ambush point, or triggering IEDs in doorways of buildings - a new Taliban tactic - we would blow our way through the perimeter of a large compound that could be seen through the trees.</span></p>
<p><span>Engineers placed a mine against the nearest wall and lit the fuse. The terrific concussion left a hole large enough for a man to climb through, past a fiercely blazing stook of cannabis - stockpiled by the Taliban - which had been ignited by the blast.<span> </span><br></span></p>
<p><span>'Try not to breath in the wacky-backy,' said the lieutenant.</span></p>
<p><span>The far wall was similarly breached; we were clear to cross another field and 'go firm' (hug the ground) along a treeline, opposite a plantation of 10ft-high sunflowers.</span></p>
<meta charset="utf-8">
<p><span><img src="https://i.dailymail.co.uk/i/pix/2009/07/07/article-1197946-059A1EAF000005DC-484_634x652.jpg"></span></p>
</div>
<div class="clear">
<meta charset="utf-8">
<strong>A soldier takes in news of casualties and the deaths of colleagues a few hundred metres away</strong>
</div>
<div class="clear"><strong></strong></div>
<div class="clear">
<meta charset="utf-8">
<p><span>Half the platoon pushed on towards a wooded water channel. As they did so, the interpreter announced the Taliban had 'eyes on' (had made visual contact) and were 'ready to attack'. Within seconds all hell broke loose again.</span></p>
<p><span>AK-47s crackled and at least one jimpy opened up in reply, interspersed with several explosions.</span></p>
<p><span>Silence followed, broken only by the shouts of squaddies and the crowing of a rooster. Then the battle began again and a green flare rose in the blue sky, above the sunflowers, to mark the enemy's location.</span></p>
<p><span>Our section caught up with the others in the wood and the situation became more clear.</span></p>
<p><span>According to the map, we had reached our first objective. But the lieutenant and some of his men had pushed on across a field only to be pinned down by the Taliban.</span></p>
<div class="floatRHS">
<a href="https://i.dailymail.co.uk/i/pix/2009/07/07/article-1197946-0594BBF6000005DC-31_306x423_popup.jpg" class="lightboxPopupLink" onclick="return false;"><img src="https://i.dailymail.co.uk/i/pix/2009/07/07/article-1197946-0594BBF6000005DC-31_306x423.jpg" height="423" width="306" alt="" class="blkBorder b-loaded"></a>
<p class="imageCaption"><strong>After a four am start soldiers from 'B' Company grab rest during a lull in the fighting</strong></p>
</div>
<p><span>The rest of the platoon, under Sgt Lee Brough, a father-of-three from Nottingham, was positioned astride the irrigation channels, partially shielded by trees. Jimpy gunners were using the canals as trenches; up to their thighs in muddy water, the weapons resting on the bank.</span></p>
<p><span>'More men are coming to help you,' the Taliban were telling their own frontline. Then came the bad news that was to throw a pall over the day's successes began to arrive over the radio from 5 Platoon.</span></p>
<p><span>A Rocket Propelled Grenade strike: casualties.</span></p>
<p><span>'Our lads?' someone asks anxiously from the canal.</span></p>
<p><span>A calm, clear voice came across the radio. What he said stunned into silence the soldiers who heard him.</span></p>
<p><span>'I need a heli(copter). I think I have lost a leg.'</span></p>
<p><span>An RPG had hit one of the vehicles supporting the Mercians' advance. Private Robert Laws, 18, of B Company 2nd Mercians, was killed and five others wounded.</span></p>
<p><span>Communications traffic began to increase. 'Eight minutes to MERT,' (medical evacuation helicopter).</span></p>
<p><span>'Keep eyes on our west. They could be moving round.'</span></p>
<p><span>'Boys, f***ing concentrate!' On time, an RAF Chinook clattered in low, just as an Apache delivered yet another strafing run on the insurgents to our front.</span></p>
<p><span>Almost immediately further bad news arrived via the radio. Two new casualties from a massive IED, both Category A - the most serious level. We had heard the deep boom a few minutes earlier.</span></p>
<p><span>One of them, Lance Corporal David Dennis, 29, of the Light Dragoons, died before he could be evacuated.</span></p>
<p><span>The men had been helping to get the initial RPG casualties loaded on to the Chinook and were blown up as they walked back to their positions.</span></p>
<p><span>'One of them's the OC, I'm afraid.' announced the radio man.</span></p>
<p><span>He was referring to the Officer Commanding of B Company, Major Stewart Hill, an inspirational leader and a man of great charm and good humour, who had been seriously wounded in the blast.</span></p>
<p><span>Before going into battle he had asked his men: 'Is it to be the insurgents' summer or will it belong to us? Of course, it's going to be ours.'</span></p>
<p><span>Then he had quoted Field Marshal Montgomery: 'Decision in action; calmness in crisis.' His men had not let him down. Now he is receiving the first-class medical care he needs. I wish him a swift recovery.</span></p>
<p><span>Among the casualties were other men I had chatted to only that morning.<span> </span></span></p>
<div class="clear"></div>
<strong><strong><a href="https://i.dailymail.co.uk/i/pix/2009/07/07/article-1197946-0599ACC5000005DC-927_634x359_popup.jpg" class="lightboxPopupLink" onclick="return false;"><img src="https://i.dailymail.co.uk/i/pix/2009/07/07/article-1197946-0599ACC5000005DC-927_634x359.jpg" height="359" width="634" alt="" class="blkBorder b-loaded"></a><span></span></strong></strong>
<p class="imageCaption"><strong>B company, 2 Mercians, attached to The Light Dragoon Battle Group pictured before the start of their Green Zone battles as part of Operation Panther's Claw</strong></p>
<p><span>There was the young officer who had allowed me to charge my laptop from the battery of his Spartan armoured vehicle; the senior NCO who'd made sure I had an extra litre of drinking water; the 18-year-old private with the cherubic face, who had joined only in April.<span> </span><br></span></p>
<p><span>He had said to me: 'I wasn't very good at school so I joined the Army. Me mum was furious I was coming here.'</span></p>
<p><span>All casualties; all within the last hour of battle as the light faded.</span></p>
<p><span>Sgt Lee Brough from 6 Platoon still needed to get 'the boss' Lt McIlveen and the other men back to the cover of the water course before darkness.</span></p>
<p><span>Four smoke bombs were fired from a mortar to cover their withdrawal and, amid furious bursts of fire, they made it safely back across the field.</span></p>
<p><span>The platoon rallied in a cucumber patch surrounded by trees. For a minute they rested, the strain of combat etched on their faces. But no time for introspection; we had to get moving, to reach a 'safe' position to make camp.</span></p>
<p><span>As we trudged, hundreds of bats swirled about our heads, feeding on the millions of mosquitoes which feasted on the soldiers.</span></p>
<p><span>After an hour, a green flare rose into the night sky from the farm compound where we would be spending the night.</span></p>
<p><span>Miraculously, it seemed to me at least, 6 Platoon was intact after a bloody day for its parent company.</span></p>
<p><span>'These young lads are just incredible,' said Lt McIlveen, as his men bedded down under the stars. 'They suck it in and go back for more.'</span></p>
<p><span>Today they will indeed be back for more in the frontline. They have lost comrades - yesterday, the death of a Welsh Guardsman attached to the Light Dragoons was also announced - but the offensive goes on.</span></p>
</div>
</div>]]>
    </content>
  </entry>
</feed>
